好的。好的，嗯。谢谢你回来。
Okay. Okay, yeah. Thanks for coming back.
我们开始吧。今天的讲座会很轻松。
Let's get started. So today should be a very lightwek lecture.
我们只会讲一点量子相关的内容。
We will only cover a little bit in quantuion.
嗯，好。然后我们希望你能参加周四的嘉宾讲座。
Yeah. Okay. And then we hope you will attend the Thursday's guest lecture. Yeah.
我们希望你能向我们的嘉宾提一些很难的问题，好吗？
We hope you ask very difficult questions to our guest, okay?
好的。在开始主要内容之前，我们先做几个选择题。
Yeah. Okay, before we start the main content, let's do a few MCC.
嗯，以下哪一项不是内存消耗的主要来源？选D，对吧？
Um, which of the following is not one of the main sources of memory consumption? D, right?
训练代码占用其实很少。
Training code is pretty minimal.
和其他任何东西比起来都很少。
Okay, compared to anything else.
好的。那么关于分段检查点，以下哪项说法是错误的？
Okay. So which of the following statement is false about grading checkpointing?
哪一个？
Which one?
A，我听到的是A。那我们一个一个来看。
A, I heard A. So let's go one by one.
在模型训练过程中应用梯度检查点可以节省GPO内存。
Apply grading checkpointing during model training could save GPO memory.
这个说法是对的，因为这正是梯度检查点的目的。
This one is true because that's the purpose of grad checkpoint.
B，梯度检查点适用于模型权重和激活值。
B, grading checkpointing applies to both model ways and activations.
第四点，就像我已经强调过的，梯度检查点只能节省激活值。
Fourth, like I already emphasized, grading checkpointing can only save activations.
梯度检查点的位置会影响所需的计算量和内存。
The location of grading checkpointing affects how much computation and memory are needed.
是的，所以你在这方面需要有策略，明白吗？
Yes, so you need to be strategic on that, okay?
所以有可能将部分激活值从内存中移除，因为它们
So it's possible to describe some of the activation from memory since they are
只在反向传播时才需要。
only needed during backward pass.
是的，这大致解释了评分检查点是如何工作的。
Yes, that's kind of the explain how grading check point works.
好的，这个需要花更长一点时间。
Okay, this one take a bit longer.
我在上一节课已经讲过这个了，对吧？
I already taught this right in the last lecture.
我想让你来计算一下。
I want you to calculate it.
好的。那么，给你这张来自非常著名的GPD-3论文的表格，
Okay. So given this table from the very famous GPD three paper,
GPD-3的激活大小是多少？2.7B。
what is the activation size of GPD three? 2.7 B.
好的，假设我们用的是GPD-3的小版本，并且我们使用的是P16，
Okay, the smaller version of GP three, assuming that we are using a P 16
还假设我们在transformer边界进行检查点保存。
and also assuming that we are checkpointing at the transformer boundary.
好，我给你1分钟来计算。
Okay, I will give you 1 minute to calculate.
嗯。
Mm.
那是哪一个？
So what one?
对，答案是C。好的。
Yeah. The answer is C. Okay.
但我想直接做计算，不过我会给你一些基本的策略。
But I want to do the calculation directly, but I will give you some so basically strategy.
这里说我们需要一个GPT-3，2.7B，对吧？
So here, it said that we need a GPT three, 2.7 B, right?
所以我们基本上是在这一行做索引，对吧？
So we basically index on this line, right?
好的，那么为了估算激活值，我们需要知道哪些参数。
Okay? So in order to estimate the activation, what parameters we need to know.
我说的是LP 16，对吧？
I said LP 16, right?
所以基本上每个数值会占用两个字节，对吧？
So basically each value will contribute to two bites, right?
而且它还说我们只关心激活值。
And it also said we only care about activation.
所以你还记得transformer的激活值吧，对吗？
So you'll still remember the activation for transformer, right?
是批量大小乘以。
It's batch size times.
序列长度，序列长度。
Sequence length, sequence lengths.
好的。再乘以三的维度，对吧？
Okay. Times times three in dimension, right?
所以基本上就是D模型。
So basically D model.
因此，你需要从表格中查找参数。
And therefore, you need to look for the parameters from the table.
那么批量大小是多少？在他们训练这个27亿参数模型时，
So what is the battery size? This table when they train this 2.7 billion model,
用的是100万的批量大小。
it used 1 million batch size.
好的。但这100万的批量大小是以token为单位的。
Okay. But this 1 million body size is in a unit of tokens.
也就是说，每个批次里有100万个token，这个信息已经浮现出来了
That is in each batch, there is 1 million tokens, this information is already surfacing the way
因为在最初的激活计算中，我们用的是批量大小乘以序列长度，
because in this original activation calculation, we use batize times sequence length,
这个BS在琥珀序列中被表征出来。
this BS is characterized in amber sequences.
这样说有道理吗？
Does that make sense?
木材序列乘以序列长度等于token数量，对吧？
Lumber sequences times sequence length equals to Number tokens, right?
好的。所以，这个乘积本质上就是1，对吗？
Okay. Therefore, this product is essentially just one, right?
好的。所以，这就是1。
Okay. Therefore, this is one.
D模型，这里告诉你D模型本质上就是在这里，对吧？
D model, this t told you that D model is essentially, um, here, right?
呃，2560。明白了吗？这基本上就像你用这个数字乘以一百万，
Uh, 2560. Okay? This is basically like you time one minion with this number,
你基本上就得到了每一层的激活数，对吧？
you essentially get the activation per layer, right?
好的。所以基本上每个transformer边界，你都会遇到这种
Okay. So basically each transformer boundary, you are going to meet this kind
激活，这种规模的激活。
of activation, this size of activation.
但问题是，在这个模型中，
But the problem is, in this model,
2.7B的GPT-3，你有很多很多层，对吧？
270 B GPT three, you have many many layers, right?
我认为这个问题是在问，我们要在每一层的边界都应用梯度检查点。
And I think this question asks that we are going to apply gradient checkpoint every layer boundary.
明白吗？也就是说每一层我们都做一次检查点，对吧？
Okay? Which means each layer, we all checkpoint once, right?
我们只保存这些，其余的全部丢弃，明白吗？
We only save them and we discard all the rest, okay?
所以基本上，我们需要把这个值乘以层数，对吧？
So basically, we need to time this value with a number of layers, right?
那2.7B有多少层？
So how many layers in 2.7 B?
你也可以从这个表格里查到，对吧？
You can also get from this table, right?
在这里，32。好的。所以基本上你再乘以32，然后把它换算成GB。
It's here, 32. Okay. So basically, you multiply another 32, and then you convert it into gigabytes.
这就是你的答案。明白了吗？很棒。
That's your value. Okay? Makes sense. Cool.
我们将在考试中问一个不同的问题。
We will ask a different question in exam.
好的，一个不同的模型，比如说Lama。
Okay, a different model, for example, Lama.
好的。我希望你能理解这一点，好吗？
Okay. I hope you understand this, okay?
很好。那么，我觉得在数学课上，我们基本上讨论了三个，
Cool. Okay, I think in math lecture, we basically, um, talk about three,
非常重要的内存优化，对吧？
very important memory ogenation right?
嗯，分级检查点、微批处理、分级累积和交换。
Um, grading check pointing, micro baatchingO grading accumulation and swapping.
我觉得在实际操作中，你们面临的挑战是，每当遇到自动内存时，
I think in practice, you are facing a challenge that is whenever you meet kind of auto memory,
你们该如何在这个领域中进行选择？
how you actually navigate this space?
我应该使用哪种策略？
Which strategy should I use?
课后我从很多同学那里都收到了这个问题。
I got this question from a lot of you after class.
我基本上想在这一页花几分钟，因为我觉得
I basically want to spend a few minutes on this slide because I think
这一页非常重要。
this slide is pretty important.
以后当你开始做这类模型时，
In the future, when you start working on these kind of models,
你基本上会需要掌握这些技巧。
you are going to basically navigate the tricks.
明白吗？所以你首先要确定理想的训练批量大小，对吧？那为什么我们要从这里开始？
Okay? So you start basically determine desired training bad size, right? So why we start with this?
因为训练批量大小是一个超参数，它会影响你的模型
Because training body size is a hyperparameter, it will affect your model
以及你最终收敛的模型准确率，对吧？
your converged model accuracy, right?
你基本上要先找出最适合你的任务的训练批量大小，这样才能
You basically want to first figure out the best training body sizes for your job that will basically
得到你任务的最高准确率。
yield the highest accuracy for your job.
明白吗？因为批量大小对于随机梯度下降来说是一个非常关键的参数。
Okay? Because Beside is a super critical parameter for sochastic green descent.
所以基本上，你会做一些超参数调整。
So basically, you do some hyperbarn tuning.
你确定一个体积大小，这个大小基本上能给你带来很好的结果。
You lock down a body size that essentially give you seems to give you very good results.
在这个例子里，我说，也许我们要用批量大小等于64来训练。
So in this example, I said, maybe we are going to train with a bit size equal to, uh, 64.
这里，这就是全局批量大小，好吗？
And here, this is the global biis, okay?
然后我们基本上就用批量大小等于64开始训练任务，并启动训练。
And then we basically start the training job with bad size equal to 64, and we launched a training.
我们用批量大小等于64进行训练。
We train with bedside equal to 64.
然后我们检查一下内存是否足够，对吧？
And then we check if we are on memory, right?
如果没有超出内存，那就没问题。
And if we don't go on memory, we are good.
我们就不需要做任何内存优化，对吧？
We don't need to do any memory orenation, right?
但问题是，也许这个模型太大了，或者你的GPU显存非常有限。
But the problem is maybe this model is too big or maybe your GPU has very limited GPU memory,
所以它会出现内存溢出的问题。
so it will go out of memory.
然后你基本上就要开始选择你想要应用哪种内存管理方式了，对吧？
Then you essentially start navigating this uh choosing which memory
你需要决定采用哪种内存优化方法，对吗？
orienting you want to apply, right?
我刚才提到了三种方法，有交换、
So there are three I mentioned, there's swapping,
有梯度累积，还有检查点。
there's grading accumulation, there is checkpointing.
那么你首先应该考虑哪一种呢？
So which one you should start thinking about first?
检查点。还有其他答案吗？
Checkpoint. Any other answer?
其实你应该从梯度累积开始。
So you should start with grading accumulation.
为什么？因为交换非常慢，你希望尽可能快地完成你的任务。
Why? Because swapping is super slow, you want to finish your job as much as possible.
而且交换的速度其实取决于内存层级的带宽。
And swapping is kind of determined by the memory hierarchy bandwidth.
我已经跟你说过了，现在的计算机，CPU内存和芯片内存之间的带宽非常低，
Which I already told you, today's computer, the bandwidth between CP memory and
所以速度非常慢。
chipping memory is very low, so it's very slow.
你需要在最后考虑这一点，然后你基本上要在
You want to consider that at the end, then you basically decide between
梯度累积和梯度检查点之间做选择。
grading accumulation or grading checkpointing.
为什么我们一开始不选择梯度检查点呢？
Why we don't start with grading checkpointing.
因为在梯度检查点中，你实际上是在用计算量来换取内存，对吧？
Because in green chain pointing, you are essentially treating flops for your memory, right?
这意味着一旦你开启梯度检查点，接下来你的训练任务
Which means that once you turn on green chain pointing, what happens is your training job is
就会变慢，对吧？
going to be slower, right?
如果不用梯度检查点呢？
Without green check pointing?
因为你用了一些计算量来换取内存。
Because you are treating some flops, treating some compute for your memory.
你不想那样做，是因为你想尽快完成你的工作，对吧？
And you don't want to do that because you want to finish your job as soon as possible,
对吧？所以你开始，嗯……
right? So you start with, um
你尝试从梯度累积开始。
You try to start with gradient accumulation.
梯度累积，我实际上是怎么操作的。
Gradient of accumulation, how I actually navigate it.
那我应该累积多少步呢？
So how many steps should I accumulate?
因为本质上，比如说，我想用全局batch size为64来训练。
Because essentially say, I want to train with a global bites out of 64.
我有很多很多选择，
I hold many many choices,
我可以用micro batch等于1，但循环64次，
I can't use a microbtes equal to one, but I loop 64 times,
得到等效的结果。
I get equivalent results.
或者我可以用micro batch等于32，
Or I can use a microbte equal to 32,
我只需要看两次，对吧？我也能得到结果。
I only look twice, right? I also get the results.
那我应该用哪一个？所以我应该总是尽量选择一个微体大小。
So which one should I use? So I should always try to choose a microbody size
基本上就是最大的微体，为什么？
that basically the largest microboy it Why?
因为如果我用更小的微体，是的，我可以解决我的内存问题。
Because if I use a smaller microbic site, yes, I can solve my memory issue.
我会得到等效的结果，但问题是你还记得
I will get the equivalent results, but the problem is you still remember
上周MCQ给你的那个例子吗？
when MCQ gave it to you last week.
问题在于你的元模型和许多许多类似计算密集型的操作。
The problem is your metamol and many many, kind of like computer intensive operations.
它们的维度会更小。我把它降到了一维。
They will have a smaller dimension. I reduced to one.
就像我说的，在GPO中，如果你给一个很小的元模型或者一个很大的元模型，
Like I said, in GPO, if you give a very small metamo or you give a big memo,
它们的计算速度是一样的。
they will compute at the same speed.
对吧？这意味着如果你给一个某个维度等于一的小矩阵，
Right? Which means that if you give a small mathema with some dimension equal to one,
GPO的利用率就会降低，对吗？
the utilization of GPO will become lower, right?
这意味着你的训练任务会被延长。
That means that your training job will be extended.
虽然你基本上会得到相同的结果。
Although you basically get the same results.
所以基本上你想最大化你可以使用的位数，对吧？
So basically you want to maximize the possible bist you can use, okay?
所以基本上，你开始搜索
So basically, you start searching
32、16、8、4，对吧？
32-16 to eight to four, right?
然后你基本上交替调整两个变量。
And you basically alternate it two variables.
一个是有效的微批量大小。
One is the effective microbess.
另一个是梯度累积步数。
The other is lab gradient accumulating steps.
好吗？你要尽量找出在不超出内存的情况下能用的最大值。
Okay? You try to figure out the one that is the biggest you can use without going out of memory.
明白了吗？这样说有道理吗？
Okay? Does that make sense?
很好。好的。
Cool. Okay.
如果你最终找到了合适的参数，那你就没问题了。
Then if you end up with figuring out something, then you are good.
这样你就算是成功了。
Okay, you have a success.
然后你会开始估算，比如用这些微生物，
Then you'll start estimating, say, with this microbes,
我要用一分钟训练一次，
I'm going to train one iteration with
然后我需要训练，比如说，一万次迭代，你想要算出
1 minute and I need to train, say, uh, ten k iterations, and you want to figure
你的任务完成时间的估算值，也就是JCT。
out an estimation of your job completion time, JCT.
你要判断这个JCT是否符合你的预期。
You try to figure out, you try to determine if this GCT can meets your expectation.
比如说，你的经理可能会要求你在一周内给出结果。
For example, your manager probably ask you to give that results in one week
如果这个速度太慢或者可以接受，对吧？
and if this is too slow or it's okay, right?
如果你觉得可以接受，那就没问题了。
And if you think it's okay, then you are good.
你可以在这里停下，对吧？
You can stop here, right?
但如果不行，呃，你该怎么办？
But if it's not, uh, what do you do?
好吧，这意味着你可能需要增加更多的计算资源，对吧？
Okay. Which means that you probably need to add more compute, right?
你需要增加更多的GPU。
You need to add more GPOs.
这个我们下周会讲。
So we'll cover that next week.
我们将进入分布式计算和并行化的世界。
We are going to enter the world with distributing machinery, paralyzation.
我们会用多个GPU来完成这个任务。
We'll use multiple GP for this job.
好吗？所以我希望你和我在这个分支上达成共识，对吧？
Okay? So I hope you and me are on the same page for this branch, right?
那如果此时你无法确定微批量
So what if at this point you are not able to figure out microbasess
能够真正不超出内存怎么办？
that can actually not go out of memory?
比如说，即使你把微批量设置为1，还是会超出内存。
For example, even if you use a microbes, equal to one, you are still out of memory.
所以这种情况是有可能发生的。
So what is this is possible.
比如说，模型实在太大了，
For example, the model is just so huge that H
100卡只有80GB内存，你要在Nama模型上训练，对吧？
100 only have 80 gigabyte you are going to train on Nama model, right?
就像我说的，Nama模型，七个模型你没法在
And the Nama model, like I said, seven model you cannot train on
单个GPU上训练，哪怕微批量等于1。
a single GP you basically equal one.
对，所以你要做的就是考虑第二个选择，也就是梯度检查点，好吗？
Yeah. So what you do is basically you start considering the second choice, green check pointing, ok?
如果这一步失败了，你就要开启绿色检查点。
You're going to turn on if this failed, you are going to turn on green check pointing.
所以你基本上就是开启绿色检查点，然后不断地重复这个过程。
So you basically turn on green check pointing and you start looping this again and again.
你会尝试找出在开启绿色检查点的情况下，单个GPU上能训练的最大microbd。
You try to figure out the largest microbd I can train on a single GPO with green check point turn
同时也要开启梯度通信。
and also with gradient communication turno.
好的，在某个时刻，你会发现一件事。
Okay. And at some point, you are going to figure out one thing.
也许你会找到一个能用的microbd，那你就没问题了，对吧？
Maybe you are going to figure out microbes that is going to work, then you are good. Okay?
你基本上会回到这一步，对吗？
You basically come back to this line, right?
你会尝试确定你的任务完成时间。
You try to determine your job completion time.
好吗？但如果你还是失败了，你就用microbd等于1。
Okay? But if you still fail what you do you basically use a microbe equal to one,
然后你开启梯度检查点，开启梯度累积。
and you turn on gradient chat pointing, you turn on gradient accumulation,
你累积了64次，对吧？
you accumulate 64 times, okay?
你还是会继续使用内存。
You'll still go on the memory.
基本上，呃，最后就是用交换空间来解决。
Then basically, uh, swapping is the last word work.
你开始把数据交换到CPU内存里，并尝试利用内存层级
You start swapping was into CP memory and you try to use memory hierarchy
勉强让这个训练任务运行下去。
to barely make this straining job work.
但一般来说，呃，这不是一个好选择，因为
But in general, uh, this is a bad choice because it's going
这可能会让你的训练任务变慢十倍。
to probably make your training job ten times slower.
如果你的任务对时间不是很敏感，那也没关系，你只是想尝试一些想法，对吧？
If your job is not very time sensitive, you are good, you just want to try out ideas, right?
你可能会在实验室的GPU上启动这个任务，
You probably launch the job on your labs GPU and
等两天后再来看结果，好吗？
wait for two days and check the results later, okay?
但如果你真的要赶上截止日期，呃，你可能需要考虑，比如说，
But if you really meeting deadline, uh, you probably need to consider, like,
优先级排序，你增加多个模型时，因为增加多个模型，你也会获得更多内存。
prioritization, you add multiples because when you add multiples, you also get more memory.
当你获得更多内存时，你基本上可以回到
When you get more memory, you can basically come back to
这种状态，你可以用更大的模型规模进行训练，最大化你的GPU利用率。
this regime where you can train with a large body size, maximize your GPU addition.
你会获得更多的浮点运算能力和更多内存。
You get more flops, more memory.
好的。所以基本上，这是一个关于如何优化内存并确保
Okay. So basically, this is a practical guide for how to optimize memory and make sure
你理解它的工作流程的实用指南，因为这真的非常有用。
you understand its workflow because it's super useful.
明白了吗？
Okay?
很好。那今天我们将继续讨论，
Cool. Okay. Today we are going to continue to talk about,
上周的话题。基本上是关于量化的。
our topic last week. So basically quantization.
我记得上周我们讨论了数据的数字表示，对吧？
I think last week, we talked lit digital representation of data, right?
所以还记得这个图吗，对吧？
So still remember this figure, right?
上周我其实没有详细解释，
I didn't explain pretty much last week, but,
我希望你们在周末稍微看了一下课件，
I hope you basically look at the slides a little bit
并且你们明白了什么是指数，什么是小数部分，以及
during the weekend and you understand what is exponent, what is fraction, and how
我们是如何在这里表示浮点数的。
we represent floating point numbers here.
这是我们的标准LP32格式，好吗？
This is our standard L P 32, okay?
那么浮点数背后的直觉是，
So the intuition behind the floating point is that, uh,
我们基本上指定了一些位来表示指数，通过改变指数的值，
we basically designate a few bits for represent the exponent and by varying the values of exponent,
我们可以让小数点在数值中左右移动。
we can move the floating point from left to right.
因此，我们有一个相当动态的范围，我们还可以基本上指定几位用于
Therefore, we have a pretty dynamic range, and we can also basically designate a few bits for
小数部分，这样我们就可以控制浮点数的精度。
the fraction so we can control the precision of our floating point numbers.
好的。为了让浮点数移动，比如说大于一或小于一，
Okay. And in order to move the floating point, you know, about one also below one,
我们需要加入指数偏置。
we have to add exponent bias.
指数偏置基本上是用八位可以表示的最大数的中位数，
Exploding bias is basically the median number of the maximum number that can be
在这个例子中就是这样。
represented using eight bits in this example.
也就是指数部分的位数。
So it's the number of bits in the exponent part.
好吗？对这部分有问题吗？
Okay? Yeah. Any questions on this part?
很好。接下来我们要做一些更具体的练习。
Cool. Then we are going to do something more excise.
好的，那么在这个图中，
Okay. So in this figure,
我给你这个方程，教你如何读取32位的浮点数表示。
I give you the equation, how to read this floating point representation in 32 bits.
我的疑问是，零要怎么表示。
My question is, how to represent zero.
好的。但看着这个方程，你会发现它根本不可能表示零，对吧？
Okay. But looking at this equation, you figure out that it's impossible to represent zero, right?
B在中间部分是一加分数，你可以看到，我们总是有一个偏置项，对吧？
B in the middle part one plus fraction, you can see, we always have bias term one, right?
乘以一个不是零的东西。
Way time something that is not zero.
所以基本上，这个方程没有像p值那样的零。
So basically, this equation does not have zeros like p value, okay?
那么怎么表示零呢？基本上，我们需要做一些非常人为的处理。
So how to read zero. So basically, we have to do some very artificial thing, okay?
所以为了表示零，我们基本上就是说，如果所有的指数都等于零，
So in order to represent zero, we basically, uh, say that if all the explosion equals zero,
我们就要把浮点数的表示方式改成那个方程。
we are going to change the floating point representation into that equation.
好的，如果你把那个方程和左边的方程比较一下，
Okay, if you look at that equation compared to the left set equation,
你会发现第一个变化基本上是在中间部分。
you'll find the first change is basically, um, in the middle part,
左边部分是“一加分数”，对吧？
the left part is one plus fraction, right?
你知道，右边部分就是分数。
You know, in the right part, is fraction.
没有“一加”，明白吗？
There's no one plus, okay?
第二个变化是在指数的平方上。
And the second change is on the power uh power two.
左边部分基本上是“指数减去偏置”。
In the left part is basically exponent minus bias,
但右边部分基本上是“一减去偏置”。
but in the right part is basically one minus the bias.
这有点人为，但这就是我们表示14位小数的方法。
Okay? This is a little bit artificial, but this is how we represent 14 point numbers.
我们把这种数叫做lambers。
Um, and we call this kind of lambers.
基本上，当所有指数位都在时，我们把这种数叫做sublomal lambers。
So basically, when all the expolen bits are there, we call this kind of lambs sublomal lambers.
好的。当指数位不存在时，我们称之为次正规数。
Okay. When the expoolen bits are not there, we call it mal lambers.
所以本质上，对于任何浮点数表示，我们有两个范围。
So essentially, for any floating point retation we have two ranges.
一个是次正规数，另一个是正规数。
One is sublomalumbers. The other is lomal lambers.
好的。这取决于指数位是否存在。
Okay. And it's determined by if the expoolen bits are there or not.
好的，明白。那么回答我之前的问题，为了表示零，你需要
Okay. Cool. So to answer my previous question, in order to represent zero, what do you
做的基本上是，你进入次正规范围，然后把指数位全部设为零，
do is basically, uh, you go into the sublomer range, and you set or expollen bits into zero,
同时，你把尾数位也全部设为零，这样就是零了。
meanwhile, you set or fraction bits into zero is basically zero.
好的，这里你去掉了那个一加的部分。
Okay. Here, you get rid of the one plus.
好的，明白了正规数和次正规数的概念后，
Okay. Cool. Then with this understanding of lomal and sublom values,
我们的问题是，最小的正数是多少？
our question is, what is the minimum positive value?
好的。那么为了确定这个所表示的最小正值，
Okay. So in order to determine the minimum positive value represented by this,
我们只讨论最小正值，是因为我们可以取负号，
we only hear about minimum positive value because we can take the minus
这样我们就能得到最大的负值，对吧？
and we get the mini maximum negative value, right?
那么最小正值是多少呢？
So what is the minimum positive value?
这基本上可以让我们了解，用这种表示法我们能有多精确，对吧？
So that can basically give us a sense like how precise we can be, right, using insenation.
好吗？所以我们只需要研究一下最小正值，
Okay? So the minimum positive value we just need to basically investigate,
呃，左边和右边，最小值分别是多少，
uh, the left hand side and the right hand, what is what is the minimum
然后我们取最小的正值，对吧？
and we'll take a minimum oppose, right?
那么在左边，我们基本上用那个公式。
So on the left hand side, we basically use that equation.
呃，我们要做的其实是，因为在左边，我们不能
Uh, What do we do is basically, um, because in left hand side, we cannot
把所有的指数位都放到箭头里。
side all the exponent bits into all the arrow.
所以我们能给指数位的最小值基本上就是一，对吧？
So the minimum value we can do for exponent bits is basically one, right?
所以，呃，我们基本上就是把这个值设为一。
So, uh, we just basically Assign this value into one.
这是我们能给指数的最小值。
That's the minimum we can do for exponent.
当然，对于小数部分，我们可以设为零。
And of course for the fraction, we can do a zero.
这样就会得到最小值。
That will give the minimum value.
把这个代入这个公式，我们就得到这个结果。
And we substitute this into this equation, we get this one.
基本上就是2的负126次方。
It's basically two to two minus 126.
这是一个非常小的值，好吧。
It's a very small value, okay.
右边我们只是用了一个不同的公式，对吧？
And on the right hand side, we just use a different equation, right?
所以，因为在右边，它是次正规数，所以这部分必须为零。
So, because on the right hand side, it is sublomal so this part must be zero.
我们可以做的是，对于这部分，我们要选择最小值，对吧？
And what we can do is for this part, we are going to choose the minimum value, right?
最小的非零值，可以吗？
Minimum long zero value, okay?
然后我们基本上得到了这个。这就是我们在次正规范围内能做到的最小值。
And we basically get this one. And this is the minimum value we can do for the sublomer range.
如果你比较这两个，很明显，右边的更小，对吧。
And if you compare this two, apparently, right hand side is even smaller, right.
所以这基本上就是我们用P 32能表示的最小正值，好吗？
So that's basically the minimum positive value we can represent using P 32, okay?
好的。我们还有一些其他人为设定的东西，
Okay. And we also have a few other artificial things,
我们为这个方向指定了一些特殊值。
artificial values we designated into this orientation.
比如，在这个例子中，所有的指数位都是1。
For example, in this example, all the exponent bits is one.
但在正常范围内，所有的指数位都是1，所有的尾数位都是0，
But in the normal range, okay all the exponent bits are one and all the fraction bits are zero,
我们基本上把这个称为正无穷大。
we basically call this, uh, positive infinity.
好吗？这个很容易理解，对吧。
Okay? This is easy to understand, right.
所以基本上这个值被最大化，而这个是零。
So basically this value is maximized, and this is zero.
我们基本上用这种表示法来表示正无穷大。
And we basically use this resentation to represent positive infinity.
同样的方法，我们只需要稍微改变一下符号位，
And the same thing, we just, um, change the sun beat a little bit,
我们就可以表示负无穷大，可以吗？
we represent the negative infinity. Okay?
同时，在非正规范围内，我们要做的是，呃，不是非正规。
And meanwhile, uh, in a subnormal range, what do we do is, um, not subnormal.
所以基本上，当所有这些值都是一时，呃，基本上，
So basically, when all this value is one, uh, basically,
我们会用，当这个符号位没有被使用时，我们会用这个来表示，
we will use and when this sunbat is not used, we are going to use this to represent,
呃，不是一个数字。
um, not a amber.
好吗？而且我们并不关心这里面的任何数值。
Okay? And we don't care about any values in this.
你可以看到这其实是很大的浪费，对吧，因为基本上我们浪费了，
And you can see this is a big waste, right, because so basically we waste,
很多很多的可能性。
many, many possibilities in this.
是的。我们用这个来表示没有木材，其实有很多浪费，对吧，
And, yeah. And we use this to represent no lumber, and there are a lot of waste, right,
因为我们本来可以用这种方式来表示其他的数值，
because we originally could use this kind of thing to represent the other values,
嗯，好，我们会在FVA中修正这个问题。
um, Okay, and we will revise this in FVA.
好，总结一下，我觉得这张表给了你一个总结。
Okay. To summarize, I think this table gives you a summarization.
所以我们有两个区间，对吧？
So we have two ranges, right?
Loom区间和sublom区间。
Loom range and the sublom range.
好吗？所以当你暴露为零时，我们基本上进入了sublom区间。
Okay? So when you exposing to zero, we basically go into the sublom range.
在次正规范围内，我们用这个公式基本上是把二进制转换成十进制，明白吗？
And in the sublomer range, we use this equation to basically convert the binary into decimal, okay?
当指数不为零时，我们进入正规范围，会用不同的公式。
And when the exponent is not zero, we go into the normal range and we use different equation.
那就是大家都知道的公式，在正规范围内。
And that's the equation that everybody knows, okay, in normal range.
好的，当指数全为1时。
Okay. And when the exponent is full.
那么基本上每个重复码是什么？
So basically every rabit is what?
然后我们保留所有这些其他的重复码，把它们用作
Then we reserve all the other all these kind of, uh repents and we use that as
正无穷、负无穷或非数。
either positive or negative infinity or not number.
尤其是在这个范围内，我们其实浪费了很多。
Okay. And especially on this range, we basically waste a lot.
对这个表格有什么问题吗？
Okay. Any question on this table?
那么你可能会逐渐明白一件事，你可以看到，
Okay. Then one thing you probably will gradually understand is, you can see,
如果我们基本上把所有的数字画在x轴上，然后我们试图，呃，
if we basically draw all the lumbers on the x axis, and we try to uh,
计算两个数字之间的距离，我们会发现这个浮点运算
calculate the distance between two numbers, we find that this floating point operation
浮点数字和定点数字是非常不同的。
flowing point lumber is quite different from fixed point numbers.
记住，在定点数中，我们基本上是在某个位置指定一个小数点，对吧。
Remember in fixed point, we basically designate a decimal point at some place right.
所以基本上，不同数字之间的距离是相等的。
So basically, we have equal distance between different umbers.
但是在浮点数中，如果我们把数值放在这条轴上，
But in flowing point number, if we put the value on this axis,
你会发现当数值很小的时候，呃，我们实际上有很高的精度。
you will figure out that when the value is small, uh, we actually have a lot of precision.
所以在这个区域内，任意两个数字之间的距离都非常小。
So the distance between any two lambers in this area is very small.
好吗？但是当数值非常大时，你可以看到，呃，两个数字之间的距离非常大。
Okay? But window value is pretty big, you can see Uh, the distance between two numbers are very big.
这意味着在这个区域精度更低。那么我们为什么要这样做呢？
That is well less precision in this area. So why we do this?
所以基本上，这是一个权衡。
So basically, it's a trade off.
我们想要表示很大的数字。
So we want to represent large numbers.
但我们也想表示非常小的，比如浮点数。
But we also want to represent very small like floating point numbers.
好的，我们需要做出权衡。
Okay. We want to trade off.
基本上，爆炸位控制动态范围。
So basically, um, the exploding best controls the dynamic range.
如果我们给它更多的爆炸位，我们就能表示越来越大的数字，对吧？
If we give it more like exploding bees we are going to represent larger and larger numbers, right?
而尾数位基本上给你精度。
And the fraction bias basically give you precision.
如果你给更多的尾数位，你就有更高的精度。
If you give more fraction bias, you have more precision.
也就是说，任意两个较小数值之间的距离会更小。
That is the distance between any smaller two small values is going to be smaller.
所以你可以表示更多的数值。
So you can represent more values.
好吗？这是一个重要的权衡。
Okay? It's essential trade off.
好吗？记住这一点，因为我们会一遍又一遍地回顾它，
Okay? And remember this because we are going to revis this again and again,
在量子机器学习中。
in quantison machine learning.
好的，有了这些，我认为我们可以更深入地探讨
Okay, with that, I think we can basically dive deeper into the true floating point representations
我们在机器学习中使用的真正浮点数表示。
we used in machine learning.
好的，这是LP 32，对吧？
Okay. And this is LP 32, right?
我觉得我们已经深入探讨过这个了。
And I think we dive pretty deep into that.
它有8位指数部分，
It has eight bits of exposed,
23位小数部分，对吧，总共32位。
23 bits of fraction, right, total 32.
因为机器学习变得如此流行。
And because machine learning becomes so popular.
所以这个法案的基本建立，我们也尝试借鉴了AE 75制定的另一个标准，
So Act basically establish we also try to leverage another standard established from AE 75,
六，我基本上指的是LP 60或16。
six, I basically LP 60 or 16.
所以，这个其实就是我们用来训练的那个。
So, uh this one is basically the one that we use to train.
用来训练语言模型，训练很多模型。
Language models to train a lot of models.
好的，呃，transformers。
Okay, um, transformers.
在这个LP 16中，我们基本上是用五位指数和十位尾数。
And in this LP uh 16, what we do is basically we use five bits of exponent and ten bits of fraction.
好的，就像我说的，
Okay. And like I said,
在上一节课，我想
I previous lecture, I think
Google提出了brain flow 16。
Google it comes up of brain flow 16.
他们做的是和FP 16相比，稍微做了一些调整，
Okay? And what they do is compared to FP 16, uh, they adjust a little bit,
所以他们把更多的位分配给了指数位，嗯，然后减少了分数位的位数。
so they give more bits into, um, this exponent bits and they go last bits to fraction.
我还说过，有强有力的实证证据表明，BF16在训练神经网络时效果更好。
And I also said that there's strength empirical evidence that this BF 16 is much
那为什么呢？
better at training neural networks. So why?
有人能给点直观解释吗？
Can anyone give intuition?
那我们可以在这里稍微推理一下，好吗？
So we can reason a little bit here, okay?
那我们来比较一下FP16和BF16。
So compare FP 16 and BF 16.
唯一的区别是BF
The only difference is BF
16会有更高的动态范围。
16 is going to have a higher dynamic range.
它可以表示更大的数值，但会损失一些精度。
It can represent larger values, but it will lose some precision.
好，那为什么这对训练有好处呢？
Okay? So why this is good for training?
因为在机器学习训练中，尤其是在训练的早期阶段，
Because in machinery training, especially in the early phase of your training,
你会得到梯度，而你的梯度会不断波动，上下起伏，非常不稳定。
you are going to derive gradits and your grading can go up and down. It's very turbulent.
明白吗？如果你的动态范围很小，那么在某一步，
Okay? And if you have a very small dynamic range, what you do is at some step,
梯度可能会轻微爆炸，甚至超出P16的动态范围，
the gradient slightly explode, okay and probably will explode beyond the dynamic range of P 16,
这样你就会得到无穷大的数值或者很多无效的数值，对吧？
then you'll go into infinity value or a lot of lumber value, right?
如果你把这些数值应用到训练中，就会毁掉你的模型，对吧？
And if you apply that value into your training, it's going to destroy your model, right?
这就是为什么，呃，谷歌发现了这个问题，然后他们提出了16位的解决方案。
That's why, uh, Google basically found this and, uh, they figure out basically bit of 16.
他们给16位浮点数分配了更多的指数位，这样可以让训练过程更稳定，
They give more exponent bits to the 16 bits of orientation, and it can stabilize the training
因为你可以表示更大的梯度，无论是正的还是负的。
because you can represent the larger gradients, either positive or negative.
这就是直觉。
Okay? That's intuition.
很酷。你在推理时会怎么做？哪种方式更好？
Cool. Any inference what you do? Which one is better?
一般来说，我会说推理更好，
In general, I would say inference,
P六更好，因为推理基本上是带有稳定器的。
P six is better because inference basically with a stabilizer.
如果你用一些边际模型，你可能会发现大多数
And if you invest some margining model, you probably figure out the most ways of
边际模型在收敛后数值都非常小。
marginy model are very smaller values after convergence.
为什么呢？
Why?
因为我们在训练过程中有很多正则化。
Because we have a lot of regulations during training.
我们确保数值不会超过某些范围。
We make sure the value will not go beyond some values.
我们会做类似裁剪之类的操作，对吧？
We'll do greening called clipping or whatever, right?
在这个假设下，推理时我们可能更倾向于使用更多的小数位。
And given this assumption, what happens is in inference, we probably prefer more fraction bits.
为什么？因为我们想要更精确的结果。
Why? Because we want precise results.
是的，我们想要更高的精度。
Yeah, we want more precision.
记住这个数字，我们希望它更精确，所以我们需要更多的小数位偏置。
Remember this figure, we want this to be more precise, so we want more fraction bias.
好的。这基本上可以让你对我们一直在讨论的这些数字有一些直观的理解。
Okay. This basically give you some intuition on these kind of lumbers we have been talking about.
明白了吗？明白。
Okay? Okay.
总结一下，如果你有更大的指数位宽，
To summarize, so if you have more exploded width,
你基本上就有了更大的动态范围，明白吗？
you basically have a larger range, dynamic range, okay?
如果你有更多的小数位宽，你基本上就有了更高的精度。
If you have more fraction width, you basically have more precision.
最终，你需要根据你的工作负载在这两者之间进行权衡。
And eventually, you want to treat off between this depending on your workloads.
好的。好的。我希望这很清楚，对吧？
Okay. Okay. I hope this is clear, right?
你明白浮点数了吗？
You understand the floating point, okay?
我们要做练习了。
We are going to do exercise.
好吗？那这个数字是什么？
Okay? So what is this lumber?
我给你两分钟时间。
I will give you 2 minutes.
也许我是这个意思，因为你拿着我的幻灯片。好吧。
Maybe I mean it because you hold my slide. Okay.
好的，那我们来一起看看吧。
Okay, yeah, let's go through it.
当你读到这种数字时，基本上要做两件事。
So when you read this kind of number, you basically start with two things.
第一，你要判断这是正规范围还是非正规范围。
One is you figure out if this is mal range or sub lomer range.
这个显然是正规数，因为你看指数位不是零，所以它是正规数。
So this is apparently normal because you look at the expoen bits and it's not zero, so it's normal.
一旦你确定它是正规数，你基本上就知道第一个公式了，然后
Once you figure out it's normal, you basically know the equation, the first equation, then
这个求和部分其实挺简单的吧？
this sum bit is pretty easy?
我们稍后会讲到这个。
We are going to talk about it later.
但你接下来要弄明白的第二件事是，关于这个浮点数，
But the second thing you want to figure out is uh, for this floating point,
你需要搞清楚偏置值，就像我刚才说的，
you want to figure out the bias value, like I said,
偏置值基本上就是这个指数位所能表示的最大值的中位数。
The bias value is basically the median the median of the maximum value that are represented
就是说由这个指数位表示的最大值的中间值，对吧？
by this exponent bis, okay?
所以前面是符号位减去，对吧？
So sine minus, okay?
然后我们再来确定指数部分。
Uh, then we figure out exponent.
那这个偏置值对于这个例子来说，这里是零，对吧，这里是一、二、三、四。
So the bias value is for this one, this is zero right, this is the one, two, three, four.
所以最大值就是，偏置值基本上是50，对吧？明白了。
So the maximum value is the bias is basically, uh, 50, okay? Okay, that makes sense.
因为实际上能取的最大值是，
Because the largest value that can be really is,
我觉得，是31，对吧？
I think, 31, right?
对。那你基本上会读取这个值，对吧？
Yeah. Okay. So then you'll basically read this value, right?
这是你得到的值，对吗？
This is the value you got, right?
然后你要减去偏置。
And you want to minus the bios.
好吗？所以用十进制表示，这个值是17，对吧？
Okay? And so in decimal, this value is 17, right?
然后减去15，得到的十进制是2。
And in -15, okay, you get two in decimal.
好吗？指数基本上就是2。
Okay? The exponent is basically two.
然后我们来算小数部分，小数部分其实很容易读出来，对吧？
And then we figure out the fraction, the fraction is pretty easy to rate, right?
这是二分之一，对吧？这是二分之一。这是四分之一。
This is half, right? This is half. This is a quarter.
好的。你基本上就是把它们全部加在一起。
Okay. You basically add all them together.
因为只有这两个值是1，所以你得到的是0.75，对吧，用小数表示。
Because only these two values are one, so you get 0.75, right, in decimal.
然后你知道这个方程，这个方程
And then you know the equation the equation
我们要用的其实就是mal方程，明白吗？
we're going to use is essentially the mal equation, okay?
所以基本上，就是负B，这其实是标准方程，对吧，所以我们有一个1加上，
So basically, it's minus B it's normal equation right so we have a one plus,
再加上这个值，这个值是2，对吧？
plus this value and this value is two, right?
所以这是一个小数，明白了吗？
So this is a decimal, okay? Makes sense.
好的，明白。在考试中，
Okay. Cool. In exam,
我会给你一个sub lomer值。
I'm going to give you a sub lomer value.
好的，那你自己算出来。
Okay. So you figure out.
好的。我们来做一个反向练习，因为这个很重要。
Cool. Okay. Let's do a reverse exercise because it is so important.
我想确保你理解这一点。
I want to make sure you understand this.
好吗？这是Google Brain的浮点数，
Okay? So this is Google Brain float,
BF16，就是我们用来训练transformer的那种。
BF 16, the one that we use to train transformers.
那么我的问题是，十进制的2.5在BF16中是什么？
So my question is, what is the decimal 2.5 in B 16.
好吗？再给你一分钟。
Okay? Again, 1 minute.
好的。
Okay.
好的，我们一起来过一遍，好吗？
Okay, let's go through it, okay?
嗯，当你解决这类问题时，直觉上你要做的是
Um, so when you solve this kind of question, the intuition is basically you try
确保你能像这样写出一个方程，因为这是浮点数的表示方法。
to make sure you compose a equation like this, because this is the representation for flame point.
然后你尝试把这个十进制数表示成某种形式
And you try to represent this decimal number into something
就是1加上某个数乘以2的幂。
that one plus something times the power of two.
明白吗？所以很明显，这是，嗯，因为这是1加上一个小数部分
Okay? So apparently, this is, um, so because this is one plus fraction and
这个值大于1，对吧？它是2。
this value is greater than one, right? It's two.
所以你至少要把它除以2。
So you have to divide it by at least two.
明白吗？所以你基本上先把它除以2。
Okay? So you basically divide it by two first.
对，你会得到1.25乘以2的一次方，对吧？
Right, you get a 1.25 times two power one, okay?
然后你可以发现这个小数部分其实是四分之一，对吧？
And then you can figure out this fraction is essentially a quarter, right?
这个指数应该是一，对吧？
And this exponent should be one, right?
好的，然后你用这个1的值，基本上就得到了实际的指数值，
Okay. So then you use this one value, you basically get the actual exponent value,
应该是这样的，所以偏置基本上就是这个，对吧？
it should be, so basically bias is this, right?
X减去127等于1，而X实际上是128，你试着用二进制表示128。
X minus 127 equal to one, and X is actually 128, you try to represent 128 in binary.
好的。我要提醒你，这里用的是B float 16，所以你有很多位用来表示指数。
Okay. That I give you basically remember this is B flow 16, so you have the many bits for expolen.
这就是为什么你得到的这个值比之前的要长一些，明白吗？
That's why you get this value pretty longer than the previous one, okay?
同时，你还有小数部分。
Meanwhile, you have fraction.
你有七位的小数部分，这里你已经知道你的小数是四分之一。
You have seven bits of fraction and here you already know your fraction is, um, a quarter.
所以基本上这里的第二个值其实就是这样。
So basically the second value here is basically.
好的。是的。我把它们都放在一起，你也有相同的位数。
Okay. Yeah. I put it all together, you also have the same bit.
这基本上就是B float 16中的这个数字。
That's basically this number in B flow 60.
酷。挺有意思的。这样的话，显然我们要开始讨论更低位的LP8了。
Cool. Okay. Interesting. With that, apparently, we start talking about even lower bits, LP eight.
LP八就是那个稍微改变了曲线的东西，因为
LP eight is the one that, kind of shift the curve a little bit because
如果你听说过Deep sik with three和一个主要的主张，他们
if you heard about Deep sik with three and a major claim they
说他们不用32位，也不用16位。
use that they don't use 32, they don't use 16.
他们用FPA八来训练他们的模型，对吧？
They use FPAight to train their model, right?
我想你能直觉地理解为什么FB八更好，因为只要你能用
I think you have the intuition why FB eight is better because whenever you can use
更低的位数来训练模型，你就会有更多的缺陷。
lower bits to train your model, you are going to have more flaws.
你的GP会更强大。
Your GP will be more powerful.
好的。事实上，他们确实非常成功，因为他们能够用这么少的
Okay. And indeed, they were very successful in the sense that they are able to use this number of
位数实现非常大的变换收敛。
bits to very large transformative convergence.
这太厉害了。为什么说太厉害呢？
That is amazing. Why is it amazing?
因为从视觉上你已经能感受到这一点，因为你可以看到这是30。
Because, visually, you can already feel this because you can see this is 30.
它很长，对吧。它可以表示很多数字。
It's so long, right. It can represent so many numbers.
好吗？这是16，虽然短了一点，但还是相当长的。
Okay? This is 16 and it's a little bit shorter but still pretty long.
但是如果你再减半，基本上就只剩下八位了。
But if you reduce this by another half, you basically only get eight bits.
好的。就像我说的，你需要保留第一位作为符号位，对吧？
Okay. And like I said, you need to reserve the first bit as a sign bit, right?
所以实际上你有七位，需要在指数和小数之间分配。
So essentially you have seven bits, that need to be allocated between expoden and fraction.
所以你能表示的数字不多。
So you don't have many numbers.
好的。你大概可以把所有数字都写在白纸上。
Okay. Probably you can just write all the numbers in white paper.
是的，这就是这个IP八能表示的所有数字。
Yeah, that's all the numbers this IP eight can represent.
好的，你可以这样想。
Okay. And you can think this.
这真的很神奇，因为本质上你只有这些数字，你可以拥有，
This is pretty amazing because essentially you only have these numbers, you can you have,
比如说，70,700亿这个数字。
say, 70,700 billion number.
你基本上需要从这个范围中选择每一个数字，对吧？
You basically need to choose each lumber from this range, right?
给每个参数设计一个数值，然后你就会得到一个
Design value to each parameter, and you will get a model that can
基本上能回答很多很多问题的模型。
basically answer many many questions.
是的，是的，这真的很有趣。
Yeah. Yeah, it's pretty interesting.
所以对于P八来说，这是一个重大的进展，
So for P eight, this one is like a major development by
英伟达想推动更低精度，对吧？
VDa B NVDA wants to push for lower precision, right?
他们这样做是因为想要保持摩尔定律，对吧？
They have this drive because they want to maintain their more law, right?
你能保持这个定律的唯一方法基本上就是使用更低的精度。
The only way that you can maintain this law is basically you use lower precision.
好吗？这里有两个标准。
Okay? And there are two standards.
一个是e4m3。
One is e4m3.
另一个是e5m2。
The other is e5m2.
基本上，e43代表指数为四位，尾数为三位。
So basically, e43 stands for exponen equals to four bits and the Mntisa equal to three.
而R基本上是指数五位，尾数两位，对吧？
And the R is basically exponent five Mantisa two, okay?
很明显，你已经可以推理出这两者的优缺点了。
And apparently not already you can already reason between the pros and cons between these two.
所以在这个e4m3中，呃，
So in this e4m3, uh,
我有四位的指数和三位的小数部分。
I have four bits of explon and three bits of fraction.
而在这个里面，我可以有五位的指数和两位的小数部分，对吧？
And in this one, can I have five explot two of fraction, okay?
我们还有一些人为的定义，比如说在CLP八中，
And we also have some artificial designations that is, for example, in CLP eight,
EM值，我们没有无穷大。
EMs, we do not have infinity.
好吗？我们还保留了一些作为基本的批号。
Okay? And we reserve some one as basically lot number.
好的。最大的EM正常值基本上是448。
Okay. And the largest Em normal value is basically 448.
好吗？这是你能达到的最大值。
Okay? That's the largest you can.
所以为了确保你的训练是成功的，也就是说在过程中，
So in order to make sure your training is successful, which means that during the throat,
训练过程中，你不能产生比这个更大的分级。
the training process, you cannot produce a grading that is bigger than this one.
否则会干扰你的机器学习训练，对吧？
Otherwise, it will disrupt your marche learning training, right?
好的，我们也可以做e52，我们还有一些人工设定的东西。
Okay. And we can also do, e52, and we have a few artificial things.
我会留给你自己去看幻灯片，好吗？
I will leave to you to check the slides, okay?
最大的PightE二值基本上几乎是这个的100倍，对吧？
And the largest PightE two value is basically like almost 100 times larger, right?
大于一百倍。
More than 100 times larger.
基本上，就是五、七、三、四、四，对吧？然后我问你一个问题。
So basically, uh, five, seven, three, four, four, okay? Then I ask you a question.
现在假设我只能用LP八，好吗？
So now, assuming that I'm only allowed to use LP eight, okay?
那我应该用哪一个来训练，哪一个用来推理？
So which one should I use for training and which one should I use for inference?
你知道答案，因为在训练时，我们需要更大的动态范围。
You know answer because in training, we want more dynamic range.
所以我们会用e52来训练。
So we would use e52 for training.
而在推理时，我们需要更高的精度。
And in inference, we want more precision.
所以我们会用E43来推理。
So we would use E for three for inference.
这基本上就是我们现在在LP八训练和推理时所做的事情。好的，明白了。
That is basically what we are doing today for LP eight, training and inference. Okay, cool.
而对于更低精度数字的追求就此停止。
And the quest for even lower precision number stops.
所以我认为Amdia正在推动整数四这个老东西。
So I think Amdia is trying to push for Integer four is old thing.
整数四其实已经是去年的事情了，
Integer four is already last year,
我觉得整数四非常成功。
I think Ing four is very successful.
如果你曾经在你的iPhone上运行过任何模型，很可能就是用整数四运行的。
If you ever run any model on your iPhone, it's likely being run in Integer four.
但是Amedia变得越来越激进了。
But Amedia has been more and more aggressive.
在下一代GPU中，他们想推动LP四。好吧。
In the next generation of GPUs they want to push for LP four. Okay.
而FP四甚至更厉害，对吧？
And FP four is even great, right?
因为如果你看这条曲线，我们一步一步来，好吗。
Because if you check this curve, let's go one by one, okay.
对于整数四来说，本质上，
For integer four, essentially,
我可以把它的值写在右边。
I can write down is value in the right hand side.
所以这里我用来补充，对吧，你们还记得补码表示整数的方法吧？
So here I use to complement, right, you still remember to compliment the reentation integers, right?
那么，嗯，呃，我把这些值写下来，如果我把这些值放在X轴上，你们可以看到，呃，
So, um, uh, I write down is values, and if I basically put these values X cess, you can see, uh,
任意两个值之间的距离是相等的。
the distance between any two values is equal.
所以，呃，基本上就是整数，好吗？
So, uh basically integers, okay?
而对于P4，媒体正在推动三种标准。
And for P four, media is trying to push for three standards.
第一个标准基本上是EYM2，指数用一位，尾数用两位。
The first standard is basically EY M two, one bit for exponent, two bits for Mantisa.
好吗？我也把数值写在这里，你们之后可以检查。
Okay? I also write the value here, and you can check later.
但是如果我把所有这些由EIM2表示的值都列出来，
But if I put all these values, that is represented by EIM two.
我基本上得到了这个范围。
I basically get this range.
你们都会发现EIM2其实不是很有用，为什么呢？因为它本质上就是整数四。
And you all find that EIM two is not very useful Y because it is essentially, Integer four.
因为我做的方法是，比如说，
Because what I do is, for example,
我可以稍微调整一下技能，它基本上就会被调整到这个范围内。
I can skill it a little bit and it will basically be skilled into this range.
基本上，LP四E二等同于整数四，但我们其实不怎么用它，
Basically, LP four E two is equivalent to integer four, we don't use that very much
因为我们经常回退去用整数四。
because we often roll back just to use integer four.
但我们还有其他几个选择。
But we have a few other choices.
其中一个是e2m1。
One is e2m1.
好吗？如果你用e2m1，并且把所有的值都放到excess里，
Okay? If you do e2m1 and you put all the values in excess,
你会发现这有点不一样，对吧？
you'll find that is slightly different, right?
因为这里我们的直径范围稍微大一点，因为我们给了Epoing更多的位数。
Because here we have a slightly larger dameter range because we give more bits into Epoing.
好的，还有第三个标准。
Okay. And there's a third standard.
基本上我们只做指数部分，不为Mantisa B指定任何bis，它只占用四位。
Basically we only do exp we don't designate any bis for Mantisa B it only hold four bits.
Es 30。事实证明，e3m0基本上就是对数值，你可以看到，所有的值都是
Es 30. And it turns out that e3m0 is basically the log values, you can see, all the values were
原因基本上就是2的幂。
reason is basically the power of two.
这些就是可能的取值。很酷。有问题吗？
And this is possible values. Cool. Any question?
到目前为止，还没有任何成功的工作是用P four训练出来的。
Yeah, by far, there's no successful job that is trained using P four.
这是一个非常好的研究领域。
This is a pretty good area of research.
所以如果你在这个领域做研究，
So if you are doing research in this area,
我强烈建议你深入研究一下。
I strongly recommend to look into this.
如果你能让它成功，我觉得你可以发表第一篇论文。
I think you can publish the first paper, if you can make this successful.
很好，这基本上涵盖了数据的数字表示。
Cool. That basically covers digital representation of data.
我认为你现在已经深入理解了我们在统一机器中如何表示数据。
I think you now have a deep understanding of how we represent data in uni machinery.
接下来我们开始讲一点关于凝聚的内容。我会重复这一页幻灯片。
Then we start talking about a bit on condensation. I'm going to repeat this slide.
凝聚是一个将输入从一个连续或较大的值集合
Condensation is a process of constraining an input from a continuous or otherwise large set
约束到一个离散集合的过程。
of values to a discrete set.
左边基本上是在尝试用少数几个可能的选项
And the left hand side basically trying to represent a continuous signal
来表示一个连续信号，对吧？
using a few possible choices, right?
右边基本上就是苹果在他们的Apple Silicon中所做的事情。
And the right hand side is basically what apples does in their Apposilicon.
他们有技术可以对数值进行比较，一旦你对图像进行比较，
So they have um technical basically contest the values, uh, and once you contact the images,
你就可以用更低的精度存储图像。
you can store the image in lower precision.
你也可以用更低精度的核心进行计算，你可以看到能耗的变化。
You can also compute using lower precision cores, and you can see what energy.
你可以看到，对于人类来说，你基本上能判断出两张图片都被保留了，对吧？
You can see, uh, for human, you can basically figure out both images are kept, right?
好的，所以在这节课里，我们要讲两个非常非常经典的内容。
Okay. So in this lecture, we are going to talk about two very, very classic.
在这门课里，我们要讲两种经典的编码技术。
In this class, we are going to talk about two classic coding technique.
第一种基本上是基于均值的条件，这种是最常用的，好吗？
The first one is basically means based condition, and this one is the most adoptive, Okay.
很可能你们所有的手机都有这个功能，明白吗？
Uh, so likely all your phones have this. Okay?
第二种基本上是线性条件，这种我认为是最强大的。
The second one is basically linear condensation, and this one is the most powerful, I would say.
所以现在很多很多的语言模型，基本上都采用了线性条件机制。
So many, many today's language model, uh, they basically follow a linear condition mechanism.
好的，我觉得我们需要注意的是，当
Okay. I think the thing that we want to pay attention is when
我们在凝聚之后应用这个编码时，存储和计算会发生什么变化？
we apply this codsation after the condensation, so what happens on storage and compute?
那么比如说，如果我们应用化学编码，存储会发生什么？我们如何存储数据？
So say if we apply chemist coniation, what happens on storage? How we store data?
因为最初你是用高精度的浮点数存储数据，而我们的目标是
Because originally you store the data in floating point in hyp precision and our goal of condiy
用现有的数据来表示高维数据。
represent hypersen data using present data.
好的，第二个问题基本上是关于计算的。
Okay. Second question is basically compute.
那么量化之后，我们调用的是什么类型的计算核心？
So after quantization, what kind of course are we calling?
比如说，如果原始数据是FP32，你用FP32进行计算，
Uh, say, if the original data is LP 32, when you compute FP 32,
你只能调用VDA的FP32核心，如果你还记得的话，
you can only call epi 32 course VDA if you remember,
我们查过VDA的产品说明书。
uh, I think we inspected the product sheet of VDA.
所以FP32的浮点运算能力，呃，比低精度的要低很多，比如说，
So the flops for Epi 32, uh, is much lower than lower precision, for example,
张量核心的FP16或者张量核心的FP8。
tensor core epis 16 or tensor core FP eight.
所以如果我们能把一些数值量化到更低的精度，
So if we are able to quantize some values into lower precision,
这可以匹配VDIa上的高性能张量核心，我们可以计算得更快，对吧？
that can match high flops tensor core on VDIa, we can compute much faster, right?
嗯，前提是我们能够保持机器学习的准确性和结果。
Uh, given that we can preserve machine learning accuracy and results.
好的。所以将来每一次，嗯，我觉得每当你阅读
Okay. So every time in the future, um, I think whenever you read
一篇量化的论文时，你都要问问自己。
a quantity paper, you want to ask yourself.
那么在我应用了这个量化技术之后，我是如何存储我的数据的，
So after I apply this quantity technique, how I store my data,
用什么样的精度，以及我是如何计算的，用什么样的核心，好吗？
in what kind of precision and how I compute, in what kind of core, okay?
我们来看看最小条件。
Let's look at the mins cosition.
当然，我们从这个四乘四的矩阵开始，好吗？
Of course, we start with, say, this four by four matrix, okay?
在这里，我假设我们用32位来存储数据。
And here, I assume that we store data in 32 bits.
好吗？那么Cemens条件的作用基本上是，嗯，我们要弄清楚，有哪些
Okay? So what Cemens condition does is basically, um, so we figure out, there are
这个四乘四矩阵中的几个数值，它们非常接近。
a few values from this four by four matrix, and they are very close.
明白吗？它们接近的意思是，我们大概可以把它们都简化成，
Okay? They are close in the sense that probably we can just reduce we can represent them all in,
比如说一两个数字。它们都非常接近于2。
say a lumber or two. They are pretty close to two.
我们基本上就是试图用一个单一的数值来表示这个单元，好吗？
And we basically try to represent the unit just a single value, okay?
并且，假设我们可以容忍这种类型的简化误差，对吧？
And, assuming that we can suffer this kind of condensation error, right?
所以在这种情况下，每个数值在简化后都会有一个小的简化误差。
So in this case, each value has a small condension arrow, after condition.
好的。那么我们该怎么做呢？
Okay. So how do we do this?
我们要做的基本上是，如果你们熟悉K均值算法的话，
What do we do is basically, we use chemis if you guys are familiar with chemist,
你们可能已经猜到我们要做什么了。
you probably already, figure out what we are going to do.
基本上，我们把这个四乘四矩阵作为输入，然后用K均值算法进行聚类。
So basically, we take this fob formtris as a as input, and we just use K means to run clustering.
好吗？K的数量还没有确定。
Okay? And the number of K is yet to be determined.
但在这里，我们假设K等于四。
But here, let's assume that K equal to four.
好吗？也就是说我们想用四个码来表示这里所有的流值，
Okay? That is we want to represent all the values all the flow values here,
四乘四，也就是16个值，只用四个码来表示。
four by four or 16 values using just four codes.
好吗？我们基本上就是找到最接近该值的码，
Okay? And we basically find the code at least clods to that value and we
然后把那个值换成那个码，对吧？
change the value into that code, right?
为了得到那个码，
In order to get that code,
我想我们要运行聚类，对吧？
I think we run cluster right?
通过聚类我们基本上就得到了那个码本。
Clustering we basically get that code book.
好的，在这里，聚类之后，我们得到了一个包含两个码的码本。
Okay. And here, after clustering, C, we get a code book of two,
1.50 和负一。
1.50 and minus one.
我们要做的基本上是对原始矩阵中的每个值，
And what we do is basically for each value in the original matrix,
我们会找到它在码本中最接近的那个值，然后把这个值替换掉。
we are going to find the one that is the Closs code on the code book and we change this value.
这基本上就是一个量化的过程。
That is basically a process of condition.
我们想用有限的选择来表示更高维度的数据，而不是更高的处理。
We want to represent a much higher dimensional data, not higher higher pressing
用有限的选择来表示数据。
data using a limited number of choices.
好的，所以在这种情况下，经过量化后，我们基本上会做一些最近邻的操作，
Okay. So in this case, after the classing and we basically do some nearest neighbor,
然后我们确定量化后的值应该是这样的。
and we figure out the quantity should be like this.
好的，明白了吗？
Okay. Makes sense, right?
很好，我们可以通过用原始值减去量化值来描述量化误差。
Cool. And we can characterize the quantat arrow by basically minus value from the original value,
这是量化箭头。
and this is the quantiting arrow.
显然，我们希望这个量化箭头越小越好，对吧？
And apparently, we want this qding arrow to be as small as possible, right?
因为，呃，直观上它会影响你最终的机器结果。
Because, uh, intuitively it will influence your eventual machinery results.
是的。好的。嗯，那我们来问个问题。
Yeah. Okay. Um no, let's ask a question.
嗯，我们的存储情况怎么样？
Uh how are we doing on storage?
如果我们做这种量化，我们真的能节省存储空间吗？可以吗？
So if we do this kind of quantudon, uh, can we actually save the storage? Okay?
最初，我们有一个4乘4的矩阵，对吧？
So originally, um, we have this four by four matrix, right?
这个矩阵里的每个元素都是用34位浮点数表示的，对吧？
So each entry in this matrix is represented using 34 bits floating point, okay?
我们有16个值，所以加起来就是512位，也就是64字节。
We have 16 values, so ten them together, we get 512 bit, which is equal to 64 bytes.
好的，那量化之后，我们的情况怎么样？
Okay? And after condon, how we are doing?
好的。那么现在，因为我们有一个包含四个值的码本。
Okay. So now, because we have a codebook, of four values.
那么为了表示四个值，我们需要多少位？
So in order to represent four values, how many bits we need?
两位，对吧？
Two bits, right?
这就是为什么每个条目我们只需要两位。
That's why each entry we only need two bits.
我们有16个条目，所以总共是32位。
And we have 16 entries, so we have 32 bits.
总的来说，我们只需要四个字节。
In total, we only need four bytes.
你可以看到，这样做大大减少了存储空间。
You can see this is a pretty aggressive reduction of stories.
同时，我们还需要表示我们的码本，因为我们的码本仍然是浮点数。
Meanwhile, we also need to represent our code book because our codebook is still a flowing point.
在这个例子中，我们有四个码，基本上每个码仍然是32位的浮点数。
So in this example, we have four codes, Basically each code is still 32 bits of flowing point.
所以为了存储码本，我们需要16个字节。
So in order to store the codebook, we have 16 bytes.
每次我们尝试计算数值时，基本上都是在查找码本。
Every time we try to figure out value, we basically index on the codebook.
所以如果我们做个对比，可以看到我们实现了3.2倍的存储压缩，这在存储上表现相当不错。
So if we do a comparison, we can see that we get a 3.2 X reduction, which is pretty good on storage.
明白了吗？这就是压缩的强大之处，对吧？
Okay? This is the power of condensation, right?
原本你无法在手机上存储这些矩阵，但现在你可以了。
Originally, you cannot store matures on your phone, but now you can.
好的。那么我们来稍微泛化一下。
Yeah. Okay. Then let's generalize a little bit.
假设我们要进行位量化。
So assuming that we are going to do bed quantuation.
这个过程决定了你的码本中有多少个码。
Okay? So this determines the number of codes in your codebook.
对，在我们之前的例子中，我们做了两位量化，现在我们做的是BD。
Right. In our previous example, we do two bit qdon and now we do BD and.
这就是为什么我们会有更多的码。
That is why we are going to have more code.
所以更多的码意味着更强的表达能力，对吧。
So more Cos means more pending power, right.
因此，量化误差会更小。
So therefore, there will be less quantitation error.
好的。但这也意味着你需要用更多的存储空间。
Okay. But that intuitive also means that you are going to use more storage.
没错。所以我们还假设对于大矩阵来说，
Right. So we are also going to assume that for big matrix,
我们有很多元素，而且这些元素数量很大。
we have a lot of entries and we have entries.
我们还要假设，你要量化的矩阵中的元素数量，
And we're going to assume that uh the number of entries in the matrix you
远大于二的幂，也就是码本的大小。
are going to quantize is much greater than two power one, that is the size of the code book.
这是很合理的，因为在实际情况中确实如此。
This is pretty reasonable because in reality, this case.
所以在左边的存储需求是32位乘以M，也就是32M位，对吧？
So for storage on the left hand side, will be to get 32 bits times M equals to 32 bts, right?
右边的话，是B乘以M，也就是MMB位，对于码本来说，我们要
On right hand side, will get the B times M equal to MMbts, for the codebook, we are going to
用32位乘以二的幂，也就是2的N次方加上5位。
have 32 bits times two power one, which is two power N plus five bits.
但就像我说的，这远大于二的一次方，所以我们基本上
But like I said, this is much greater than two power one, so we are going to basically
认为我们不会计算这个，因为这是一个很小的值。
think we are going to not count this because this is a small value.
好的。那么压缩率基本上是32除以NM，
Okay. Then the reduction rate is essentially 32 divided by NM,
也就是等于32除以N再乘以压缩率。
which is equal to 32 divided by N times the reduction.
这基本上就是K均值压缩的效果。
This is basically the power of KMs condensation effective.
我直接给你一个N倍的压缩，这个N基本上就是，嗯，
I directly give you a reduction by factor of N, and this N is basically, um,
你想选择的码本。有什么问题吗？
the code book that you want to choose. Any question?
好的，嗯，这基本上让你了解如何用K均值进行基本压缩。
Okay. Um, uh, this basically give you a sense like how way to basic condition using Kemins.
但是你可能会问，如果我用这种压缩方法，那神经网络训练怎么办？
Okay. But you probably ask if I do this kind of condition, what I do for neur network training?
因为在神经网络训练中，我们需要做前向和反向传播。
Because in neuronal training, we are going to do forward and backward.
在反向传播过程中，比如说在met Mol上，我的metamol XM Y的值会发生什么呢？
And during backward, what happens is, uh, my values on the met Mol, for example, for metamol XM Y,
我的X和Y的值会根据梯度距离进行更新。
my values on X and Y is going to update it by the grading distance.
所以我做的就是这些。这其实很直接，对吧？
So what I do. So this is pretty straightforward, right?
我们首先对权重进行量化。
So what we do is, we first apply quantisation on the waves.
然后，对于权重，假设我们得到了梯度，这些梯度就在这里，
And then, uh, for the was, assuming we are going to get the gradients and their gradients are here,
我们基本上会按照聚类的结果来处理这些权重，
and we are going to basically follow in the um clustering results on the was,
我们会为每个参数的梯度指定相同的颜色，好吗？
we are going to designate the same color, um, for each each each parameters we gradient, okay?
然后我们把它们分组在一起，好吗？
And then we group them together, okay?
我们生成一个向量，用来更新码本。
And we generate a vector that's trying to update the codebook.
好的，然后我们基本上会把每个条目上产生的这些小值都减少。
Okay. And we basically reduce all these, um, small values, produced on each entry of
使用EMIS聚类结果得到原始权重。
the original weight using the emis castering results.
嗯，这基本上就是我们要应用到代码本上的更新，其他也是一样的。
And, uh, this is basically the update that we are going to apply to the codebook and same thing.
当我们更新参数时，我们会应用一个学习率，
As as we update the parameters, what do we do is we are going to apply a learning rate and
我们用这个来更新代码本中的中心点。
we use this to update our centro in the codebook.
这个中心点其实就是EMIS聚类的结果，基本上就是我们的编码。
So this centre is basically the results of the emis clattering. Basically our codes.
我们会对编码做一些小的更新。
We are going to update codes a little bit.
直观理解就是，随着参数的更新，
So the how intuition is basically as our parameter being updated,
我们的聚类中心也会同步更新。
we are also updating our cluster centros.
好的，总之，我们要确保我们的聚类结果依然合理。
Okay. So basically, we'll make sure that our condensation still makes sense.
关键是K均值算法依然是有意义的。
The key means we still makes sense.
好的。那么这在实际中是如何运作的呢？
Okay. So how do this work in practice.
好的？人们已经把这个方法应用到了，比如卷积神经网络和各种神经网络中。
Okay? And uh, people have been applying this into, say, conversion neural networks
各种类型的神经网络都可以应用这个方法。
and all kinds of neural networks.
正如我们所看到的，我们可以有效地选择量化的比特数，这样就能
And as we can see, uh, we can effectively choose a lumber bits to quantize and that will give
给模型权重带来压缩率。
us a compression rate for model weights.
正如我们所看到的，这非常强大，对吧？
And as we can see, this is pretty powerful, okay?
所以如果我们把权重的数量减少五倍，我们大致上
So if we reduce the lumber weights by five times we roughly
在推理时不会损失任何准确率。
we do not lose any accuracy at inference.
这非常不错。如果我们要减少码本中的比特数，
Which is pretty good. And if we're going to reduce the lumber Bs in the code book,
我们的准确率在某个点上就会下降。
our accuracy is going to decrease, at some point,
精度基本上会大幅下降。
the accuracy will basically decrease, very drastically.
但我们并不希望这样，我们基本上想要保持在这个范围内。
But we don't want to we want to basically touch this regime.
这实际上变成了另一个超参数调优的工作。
This becomes another hyper primary tuning job, basically in practice,
你需要调整这个码本的数量，以确保你找到最大的，
you want to tune this number of codebooks to make sure you find the largest,
呃，转换率，同时不会降低你的精度。
uh, conversion rate, which does not decrease your accuracy.
这也意味着在今天的神经网络中，有很大的压缩空间。
This also means that in today's neural networks, there are a lot of space for compression.
许多参数其实是相当重复的。
Mony parameters are quite repetive.
所以这就是为什么量化效果相当不错。有问题吗？
So that's why quantity works pretty well. Any question?
很好，我们还可以把权重值及其直方图可视化出来。
Cool. We can also visualize basically weight values their histogram.
量化之前，你可以看到我们的权重值是这样的。
Before qdenation you can see our weight value is looking like this.
Xs 是权重值以及折扣的方式。
Xs is weight values and the way discount.
有几件事情你需要注意。
There are a few things you want to notice.
首先，在量化之前，我们的数值是相当连续的。
One is, before quantuation, our values are pretty continuous.
它基本上分布在一个连续的空间里。
It's basically spread across continuous space.
第二点你要注意的是，几乎没有值是零。
A second thing you want to notice that there are very few values as zero.
这基本上是在新的网络上。
Uh, this is basically on new works.
量化之后，就像我刚才说的，还记得我的老师的图吗，我们做的事情其实是
After condon, like I said, still remember my teacher figure, what we do is basically we represent
用离散值来表示所有的连续值。
all the continuous values using the discrete values.
你可以看到，和之前相比，现在只用了很少的几个数值。
You can see there are just a few values that is used, compared to a previous one.
如果我们用这种方法来训练，也就是稍微修改一下我们的代码，我们就可以看到。
If we use this kind of trick to do training, that is we update our code a little bit, um we can see.
我会在这两个之间轮流，对吧？
I'm going to rotate between these two, right?
你可以看到这些代码。
You can see the codes.
所以基本上，每次更新迭代后中心都会稍微移动一下。
So basically the central is slightly shift after every iteration of update.
好的，明白了。就像我说的，你用了多少位？
Okay. Cool. Okay. And like I said, how many bits you use?
这是一个超参数调优的问题。
This is a hypergrimary tuning, question.
所以你需要找到在压缩率和
So you have to figure out the sweet spot that best trade off between, uh, compression rate and
你的机器学习模型准确率之间最佳的平衡点。
your march learning model accuracy.
这基本上是出自一篇非常著名的论文的结果，
So this basically is a result from a very famous paper,
深度压缩，我已经推荐你阅读了。
deep compression, which I give to you as a reading.
好的，就是那篇开启了所有这些讨论的论文。
Okay. That is the paper that starts all this denation.
好的。我记得这篇论文的作者基本上是麻省理工学院的教授。
Okay. And I think the author of the paper is basically a professor at MIT.
他在做去噪方面非常有名，顺便说一下，他有一家公司被英伟达收购了。
He's very famous in doing denation and he has a company being acquired by NVDA, by the way.
英伟达真的很喜欢他。
NVDA really likes him.
是的，而且那笔交易也相当不错。
Yeah. And that deal is pretty good, by the way.
还记得我跟你说过这件事吗？
Remember I told you that Okay.
AutoML，基本上就是下周做嘉宾演讲的那家公司，专注于搜索领域。
The AutoML, basically the guest speakers company next week in search area.
他们的公司叫AutoML。
Their company is called AutoML.
他们也被Nvidia收购了，就是这个图的创造者，
They were also acquired by N media, the creator of this graph,
condensation，他的公司也被Nvidia收购了。
condensation, his company is also acquired by NMDia.
但是这个人的公司收购案比OctoMail的交易好得多。
But this guy's company acquisition deal is much better than Octo Mails deal.
Yeah, you can do some Google search later.
Okay. Cool. The figure here basically tells you that you want to trade off between,
uh, number of bits you use and accuracy.
You want to tune this a little bit.
Okay, so in practice, how does this screen condidon works, um in runtime?
What do we do is basically, um, we start with tact with R code book.
And every time when we try to do computation, uh, we still need to decode the width.
Using our code book and context like a lookup table to get the width, real width.
So remember this width is a value from the code book a code from the code book and the code
is still in flowing point.
这意味着我们必须在代码本中将索引解码为浮点值，
Which means that we have to decode our uh index into flowing point values in the code book,
然后我们在浮点运算中执行算术运算。
and then we perform arithmetics in floating point arithmetics.
这意味着即使你应用了这种化学凝聚方法，
That means that even if you apply this kind of chemit condensation,
你仍然在使用你的浮点核心。
you are still using your floating point core.
好的。是的，总结一下，基本上在存储方面，我们节省了很多。
Okay. Yeah. So to summarize little bit, so basically for storage, we save a lot.
基本上我们不需要保存所有原始的浮点值。
We basically we do not have to save all the original floating point values.
我们基本上只保存索引，索引。
We basically save the index, the index.
但在计算时，我们仍然需要在运行时即时解码，并尝试调用我们的浮点
But for computer, we still need to decode at runtime on the fly and we try to call our floting point
核心来计算结果，对吧？
course to calculate results, okay?
好的，这基本上就回答了这个问题。
Okay. That basically fills this question.
所以在存储方面，我们会使用整数，同时我们还有一个非常小的浮点码本。
So for storage, we are going to do integer with also we have a very small floating point code book.
而在计算时，我们会回退到使用浮点运算。
And for computer, we roll back to use floating point arithmetics.
好的，有什么问题吗？有。
Okay. Any question? Yeah.
是的，非常好的问题。
Yeah. Very good point.
所以在Kemin的讨论中，你面临的基本上是你的计算会变得更慢。
So in Kemin conversation, what you face is basically your compute will be even slower.
为什么？因为与原始的计算方式相比，你增加了一个查找表，
Why? Because compared to the original form of computer, you add a lookup table,
而查找表基本上会让你的计算变慢。
and the lookup table will basically slow down your computer.
但这意味着，正如我刚才说的，存储压缩率非常激进。
But the meaning is basically, like I said, the compression ratio for storage is very aggressive.
所以在很多很多设备中，如果你的存储有限，
So in many many devices, if you have limited storage,
但你的计算能力还可以，你就会想要这样做。
but you have okay compute, you want to do this.
一个例子就是在你的iPhone上。
One example is on your iPhone.
你的iPhone内存非常有限。
Your iPhone has very limited memory.
你想要编写你的模型，使用非常有限的内存，嗯，
You want to write your model, use a very limited memory, um,
呃，但你可能在电力和计算能力上没什么问题。所以用这个方法。对。
uh but you're probably okay with the power and compute. So use this one. Yeah.
你基本上就是要非常激进地把你的模型压缩成更小的模型。
You basically try to compress your model very aggressively into smaller model.
好的，明白。这就是Kemi条件，而这个chems codon在
Yeah. Okay. Okay, that is Kemi condition, and this chems codon is most powerful on
上一代神经网络中是最强大的。所以基本上是cob ont。
the last generation of neural networks. So basically cob ont.
现在，人们在玩语言模型，这就把我们带入了这个线性codinon。
And today, people play with language models, and that brings us into this linear codinon.
而这个near condition非常强大，因为有很多方式
And this near condition is very powerful because there are many ways that
我们可以进行线性codiation。
we can do linear codiation.
但我不会讲得太深入。
But I'm not going to dew too deep.
我会给你一个关于这个原理的高层直觉。
I'm going to give you a high le intuition how this works.
也许在下一节课，
And maybe in the next lecture,
我会告诉你我们在语言模型中常用的条件度量方法。
I'm going to tell you what are the common condition measures we use for language model.
但本质上，它们都属于线性量化。
But essentially, they all fall into linear codation.
好的，所以我们再次从一个用32位表示的4x4矩阵开始。
Okay. So again, um, we start with our four by four matrix, represented using 32 bits.
那么，我们需要条件的直觉是这样的。
Okay. So the intuition we need condition is this.
在这里，我尝试应用线性量化，并尝试对
So So here, I'm trying to apply linear quantitation, and I try to quantize
我原本用32位表示的权重进行量化为整数值。
my original weights in 32 bits into integer values.
我的目标输出值是整数。
My target output value is integers.
但就像我说的，量化数量其实是一个很宽泛的概念。
But like I said, inar quantity is pretty general.
你也可以选择不同的目标值。
You can also choose different target values.
比如说，你可以把32位量化成8位整数，
For example, you can quantize from 32 bits to eight bits of integer,
4位整数，或者你也可以把它量化成，比如说，从LP32到LP16，或者P32到FV8。
four bits of integer, or you can quantize it into, say, from LP 32 in LP 16 or P 32 into FV eight.
这取决于你选择的目标是什么。
It depends on how you choose your target.
但在这里，我给你最激进的一个例子，就是我想把它量化成整数。
But here, I give you the most aggressive one that is I want to quantize it into integers.
在这里，我想把它量化成，基本上，就是我这里表示的整数，
And here, I want to quantize it into basically, uh the integer I represented here,
2位整数，也就是4个数值。
two bit integers, four values.
好的，所以我做的基本上就是，嗯，嗯，我尝试
Okay. So what I do is basically, um, um, I try to
把我原来的浮点数值缩放到一个新的范围里。
scale my original floating point value into a new range.
这个新范围是由我选择的目标范围决定的，比如在这个例子里，
And this new range is determined by my choose target range, for example, in this example,
我只有这些数值，
I just have these many values,
2位整数。
02 bits of integer.
为了进行缩放，我们要遵循的方程基本上是线性映射。
And in order to scale it, the equation we try to follow is basically a linear mapping.
也就是说，我们基本上要减去某个值，我们把这个值叫做零点。
That is, we try to basically minus it by some value, and we call this value zero point.
好的。然后我们用一个浮点值对其进行缩放。
Okay. And then we scale it by a floating point value.
所以基本上，我们是把原始范围压缩到一个新范围里。
Okay. So basically, we are skinning original range into a new range.
在新范围里，数字被重新表示。
And in the new range, numbers are represented.
你需要的选择更少了。
You need fewer choices.
好的，你可能想知道我们是如何确定这个零点和缩放值的，
Okay. You are probably wondering how we determine, um, this zero point and also this scale,
我们很快就会弄明白了。
we are going to figure out pretty soon.
但在我们计算质量之前，
But before we figure out the mass,
我想先好好描述一下这个零点和刻度。
I want to properly characterize this zero point and scale a little bit.
好的。那么在这里，我们其实可以用这个方程来表达这个量化过程。
Okay. So here, we can actually express this skinning process as this equation.
嗯，我保留了我的原始值，也就是R，
Um, I hold my original value which is R,
R具有很高的精度。
R is at a high precision.
我保留了我的目标值，也就是量化值Q。Q代表量化值。
I hold my target value which is quantat value, which is Q. Q stands for quantas.
所以我的直觉是，如果我把原始值映射到Q上，
And so my intuition that, if I antact my original value into Q,
我仍然可以把量化值恢复成原始值，这样我就能保持精度。
I can still recover the quantat value back into the original value so I can preserve the accuracy.
好的，接下来方法是
Okay. And the way
我恢复的过程基本上是按照这个线性变换进行的，也就是我要
I recover is basically following this uh, linear transformation that is I'm going to
首先减去u偏置项Z。
first minus u bias term Z.
这基本上代表了新范围内的零点。
And basically represents zero point in the new range.
好的，然后当我从Q中减去这个值后，
Okay. And then once I basically minus the value from the Q,
我会把它缩放回我的原始范围。
I'm going to scale it back to my original range.
好的，显然如果你想应用这个近似条件，
Okay. Apparently, if you want to apply this near condition,
你需要确定两个关键参数，一个是Z，
you have two critical parameters to determine one is Z,
也就是新目标范围内的零点是什么？
or what is zero point in the new target range?
另一个是缩放因子，
The other is the skinning factor,
S。这意味着对于近似条件，
S. Which means that for near condition,
嗯，你总是需要携带两个参数。
Uh, you always carry two parameters.
好吗？因为如果你想应用这种空气单位，你必须携带这两个数值。
Okay? Because if you want to apply this kind of air unit, you have to carry these two values.
所以如果你进入Hugging阶段并检查这些，呃，
So if you go into Hugging phase and you check those, uh,
看，语言模型，特别是上下文版本，你去检查它们的配置。
see, language models, especially context version, and you check their config.
除了那些像lumber heads、隐藏维度等等，
Uh, in addition to all those kind of, like, lumbar heads, uh, hidden dimensions, et cetera,
标准的语言模型配置，你很可能会看到这两个数值。
standard language model configurations, you probably will observe these two values.
就是接触点和技能。
So contact point and, um, and skill.
对于你自己，将来你想发布你的模型，在接触工作中，
And for yourself, in the future, you want to release your model, in contact working,
你也需要发布这两个数值。
you also need to release these two values.
否则，别人无法复现你的结果。好的，明白了。
Otherwise, people cannot reproduce the results. Okay. Cool.
有两个关键参数。
There are two critical parameters.
一个是零点？另一个是比例。
One is zero point? The other scale.
好的，就像我说的，
Okay. Like I said,
Q 是整数，这里我选择我的目标值为整数。
Q is integer here I choose my target value as integer.
我的原始点 R 是浮点数。
My original point, R is floating point.
对于 Z，这基本上是一个数量参数，因为它是目标范围的零点，
For the Z, this is basically one quantity parameter because it's a zero point of a target range,
所以它必须是整数，这个 Z 的含义基本上是我们允许实数 R，
so it must be integer, the meaning of this Z is basically we allow real number R,
就是在左边等于零的那个，可以被
which is on the left hand side, which is equal to zero be represented
目标范围内的某个整数 Z 表示。
by a antat integer Z in the target range.
好的，然后我们再把它转换回来，这就得到了 S。S 是一个浮点数，
Okay. And then we screw it back, and that gives us S. S is a flowing point,
这就是我们调整回去的量化参数。
and that is the quantaing parameter that we screw the value back.
好的。从几何角度来看，基本上就是这样。
Okay. And geometrically is basically this.
我让你看几秒钟这个图。
I'll let you look at this for a few seconds.
所以一旦你看到这个图，你基本上就明白我们在做什么了，对吧？
So once you see this figure, you will feel you basically understand what we are doing, right?
基本上，我们是在做某种归一化处理。
So basically, we are doing some sort of normalization.
我们试图把原始范围内的数值归一化到一个更小的目标范围。
We try to normalize value that is in original range into a smaller range target range.
是的，我们试图对齐一些内容。
Yeah. We try to align a few things.
比如说，我们试图对齐原始范围内的均值，
For example, we try to align the mean value in my original range,
原始范围内的最大值和目标范围内的最大值。
the maximum value in my original range and the max in my target range.
我们还试图对齐一些内容，比如这两个范围之间的零点。
We also try to align a few things, for example, zero point, between these two ranges.
好的。比如说，如果我们做整数压缩，嗯，如果我们选择不同位数的整数，
Okay. And for example, if we do integer condensation, um and if we choose different bit of integers,
那么我们在目标范围内会有不同的Qmax，对吧？
we will have different Qmax in the target range, right?
这是为了补充说明，明白吗？
This is to complement, okay?
然后你可能就会开始有一些问题了。
Then you probably start asking questions.
那如果我有一个张量，我的张量有多少不同的取值？
So if I have a tensor, my tensor, how many many different values?
我该如何基本上确定参数，
How can I basically figure out the parameters,
Z和S，这样我才能把它量化到这个目标范围里。
Z and S so that I can quantize it into this target range.
比如说，如果你选择了四位整数。
For example, if you choose probably four bit integer.
好的，我们来做一下这个例子。
Okay. Let's do that. Okay.
那你怎么确定S和Z呢？
So how do you determine S and Z?
所以这个很简单，对吧？
So this is pretty simple, right?
我们只需要在数学上稍微操作一下。
We just need to play a little bit in mathematics.
好的。所以我们有原始值，也就是矩阵，
Okay. So we have our original value, which is, matrix,
然后我们尝试找出矩阵中的最大值，比如说RMax和Rmin，对吧？
and we try to figure out the maximum value in a matrix, for example, which is RMAx and Rmin, right?
然后我们按照这个线性变换，把它测试到新的整数范围里，
And we follow this linear transformation, we try to test it into the new integer range and we
并且我们尝试用新的数值，通过这个线性变换
try to use the new value in the new text value to recover following this linear transformation
再恢复回原始值。
back into the original value.
这样就得到了两个方程，对吧？
So that gives two equations, right?
所以原始范围中的RMAX等于S乘以Qx减去Z，对吧？
So RMAX in the original range equals to S times Qx minus Z, right?
我们试图让最大值对齐，
That we try to align the max value,
RM等于时间。
RM equals to times
Q Man min Z，这就是我们试图对齐均值的方式。明白吗？
Q Man min Z that is what we try to align the mean value. Okay.
这就像一个方程组，对吧？
And this is like a system of equations, right?
你有两个未知数，也有两个方程，所以你可以解出来。
You have two unknown and you also have two equations, so you can solve it.
我们只需要稍微操作一下。
And we just play a little bit.
我们把这两个方程相减，然后做一些变换，
We minus these two equations, and we do some transformation,
我们就能算出S。S基本上等于
we'll figure out S. S is equal basically
RMAXRM除以QMS，M的Cmin。
RMAXRM divided by QMS, M's Cmin.
基本上通过这个方程你就能得到它。
Basically from this equation, you get it.
这就是man addi，有点像罗马式的加法。
This is man addi, kind of roman addition.
好的。嗯，让我们来做个练习。
Okay. Yeah. Let's do a practice.
我有一个4x4的矩阵，我的目标范围是两位整数。
So, I have a matrix four by four and my target range is two bit integer.
在两位整数中，我只有四个值，我在这里表示，负二是最小值，
In two bit integer, I only have four values, which I represent here, minus two is mean value
一是正数，一是最大值。
and one is positive one is the max value.
我想用线性压缩把这个矩阵量化到这个范围，我该怎么做？
I want to use linear condensation to quantize this matrix into this range, what I do?
所以我首先要找出这个矩阵的最大值和最小值，对吗？
So I first figure out the R max and min, right? From this matrix.
好吗？这个矩阵，嗯，最大值是2.12，对吧？
Okay? This matrix, um, the maximum value is 2.12, right?
平均值是-1.08。
The mean value is -1.08.
好的。然后我基本上用这个公式。
Okay. Then what I do is basically I use this equation.
好的。我代入这些数值，同时我也找出了这里的平均值，
Okay. I substitute the values, and also I figure out and the mean value here,
然后我得到了我的S。我的蒙皮因子基本上是1.07。
and I get my S. My skinning actor is essentially 1.07.
好的，非常简单。同样地，一旦我们有了这个值，我们就可以算出Z值，
Okay. Pretty simple. And same thing, once we have this value, we can figure out the Z value,
也就是Z零点。
which is Z zero point.
我们要做的基本上就是稍微调整一下这个方程，
What do we do is basically we play around this equation a little
做一些变换，我们就能算出Z。
bit and do some transformation and we can figure out Z.
因为就像我说的，Z是在目标范围内的零点。
Because like I said, the Z is zero point in the target range.
在我的例子中，我选择了整数。
And in my example, I I choose the integer.
在我的目标范围内，我只有整数，所以我必须在这里取整。
In my target range, I only have integer, so I have to take around here.
好的，很棒。同样地，我们也可以用这个例子来做练习。
Okay. Cool. Similarly, we can do exercise for this example.
嗯，我基本上用这个方程来求Q均值和I减去
Um, I basically use this equation where I try to figure out Q mean and I minus
M除以S，然后我算错了。
M divided by S from it and I take a wrong.
好的。所以cumin是负二，对吗？
Okay. So cumin is minus two, right?
我已经知道我的army是那个值了。
And I already know my army is that value.
在我之前的幻灯片中，我算出了
In my previous slide, I figured out the value of
S的值。我基本上把它们代入，然后得到我的零点，也就是负一。好的。
S. I basically substitute them and I get my zero point, which is minus one. Okay.
所以在这里，当我们尝试把这个给定的矩阵量化到目标范围并变成整数时，
So therefore, here, when we try to quantize this given matrix into this target range to be integer,
我们基本上用的是S等于1.07，Z等于负一的数值。
we basically use a value where S equals to 1.07 and Z equals to minus one.
好吗？如果你量化你的模型参数，你也需要算出这些数值，然后
Okay? And if you quantize your model parameters, you also want to figure out the values and you
把这些数值写进你的模型里。
write down these values into your model.
每次你都要从这些数值中恢复出来。
Every time you recover that from those values.
好的。那么让我们进入本次讲座的最后部分。
Okay. Then let's come to our last part of this lecture.
所以我们想把近似条件应用到matma上，请问可以吗？
So we want to apply near condition to matma please.
如果可以的话，那当然没问题。
If Yeah, that's possible.
是的，是的。
Yeah. Yeah.
这是个很好的问题，这部分我们会在下节课中讲到。
That's a really good question. So that is a part that we are going to cover in the next lecture.
这叫做训练后凝聚。
So that is called posttraining condensation.
你有几种选择。
You have a few choices.
你可以为每个张量选择不同的SNZ。
Okay? You can choose a different SNZ for each tensor.
你也可以为整个模型选择一个常数SNZ。
You can also choose a different you can just choose one constant SNZ for entire model.
这就叫做校准凝聚。
So this is called calibration conation
你需要根据在精度上的损失来校准S和Z的值。
You want to calibrate the values of S andZ depending on how much you lose on the codaon accuracy.
明白了吗？所以很明显，如果你进行预张量量化，
Okay? So apparently, you can know that if you do pretensal condensation,
你的精度会更高，对吧？
you are going to have a higher accuracy, right?
如果你对整个网络和所有输入数据只用一个SN Z，
If you do one single SN Z for all the ways and activations for the entire network and
那么你的损失会更大，对吧？
the entire input data, you are going to lose more, right?
所以这是一个权衡，所以人们可以使用预张量量化或者整个模型量化，
So that is a trade off, so people can use pretensior conduon or entire model codenonO they
他们可以找一个校准数据集。
can figure out a calibration dataset.
他们只是根据校准数据集来量化。
They just quantize depending on the calibration data set.
或者他们也可以用一些更激进的方法，比如按通道量化。
Or they can use, some aggressive ones, for example, per channel.
我有一个矩阵，当我遍历通道时，
I have a matrix where when I'm meeting the channel,
我只是试图为每个通道找出S和Z。
I just try to figure out S and Z for each channel.
我甚至可以按组进行条件处理。
I can even use per group conidation.
这样，我就能发现，这组数值它们非常接近，
That, I figure out, okay, this group of value they are pretty close,
所以我应该为这组指定SNZ。
so I should designate SNZ for this group.
但对于那一组，它们差异很大。
But for that group, they are quite different.
所以我为不同的组指定不同的SNZ。这样说有道理吗？
So I disign different SNZ. Does that make sense?
显然，当你做更细粒度的条件处理时，复杂度会更高。
Apparently, when you do more fine grain condation you are going to it's going to be more complex.
好的。我觉得我们会在下一节课简单讲一下这个内容。
Yeah. Okay. I think that we'll cover that briefly in the next lecture.
我能告诉你的是，Fama模型，我们用很多流行的条件，基本上就是po tensor。
The thing I can tell you is Fama models, what do we do with many popular condi basically po tensor.
好的，明白。在这里，我们做la X，这样也可以。
Yeah. Okay. Cool. Here, we do la X that's okay.
我们有Y等于W和X，我们想要应用我们的凝聚方法。
We have Y equals to W and X, and we want to apply our condensation.
记住，在压痕讲座的开始，
Remember, at the beginning of denting lecture,
我说过，你需要弄清楚两件事，对吧？
I said, you want to figure out two things, right?
一是你如何存储数据。这一点很清楚。
One is how you store data. This one is pretty clear.
你存储数据的方式是存储目标区间的值，这些值应该是整数。
The way you store data is you store the target range values, which is to be integer.
你还会根据所用方案存储SNZ。
You also store off SNZ depending on which scheme you use.
问题是，凝聚后我们用什么样的算术运算来计算。
The question is, what kind of arithmetic course we use to compute after conation.
那么我们做什么呢，呃，在原始的Y等于X中，我们用的是浮点数。
So what do we do is, uh, in the original Y equals to X, we use floating point.
现在我们应用了凝聚方法。
And now we apply condenation.
现在，假设我们做某种潜在的编码。
Now, assuming we do some kind of a potential coddation
然后我们会得到SW、SX、w和ZX。
and we are going to get SW and SX and w and ZX.
基本上我们对它们进行了归约。
We basically subsue them.
好的，然后我们做一点变换。
Okay. And we do a little bit transformation.
我们发现我们的计算基础变成了这样。
We find that our computation based becomes this.
这里，QW和QX分别是量化后的权重和输入X，QY是量化后的输出。
Here, QW and QX is the quantized weight and input X, and QY is the quantized output.
我们需要对输出进行量化的原因是因为这是神经网络的一层，
The reason we need quantize output because this is the layer
并且它会传递到下一层。
of neural work and that proceed to next layer.
好的？我们再做一些操作，就得到了这个方程。
Okay? And we do a little bit like manipulation and we get this equation.
好的？我们来仔细分析一下这个方程。
Okay? Let's try to inspect this equation a little bit. Okay.
首先我们注意到，这一部分我们可以提前计算。
So the first part we notice that for this part, we can pre compute it because
权重是固定的，推理时不变。
the weight is fixed, spit inference.
所以我们可以预先计算权重的处理方式。
So we can pre compute how we tact the weight.
对于X来说，比如说，如果我们用校准数据集，我们可以选取一个数据集。
And for X, we can also, for example, if we do calibration data set, we can take a dataset.
对，我们假设会对数据集里的所有数据使用相同的scale和zero point。
Right. We assume we are going to use the same skill and zero point for all the data in the dataset.
好的，那么利用校准数据集，我们基本上可以确定一个数值。
Okay. Then using calibration data set, we can basically figure out a value
或者说，基本上是ZX，对吧。
or the basically ZX Right.
那么有了校准数据集和固定的权重，我们基本上就可以确定
Then with calibrating data set and with fixed weights, we basically figure out that all
橙色框里的所有值，y是常数。
the values in the orange box, y constant.
它们不依赖于输入。
They are not dependent on the input.
所以我们基本上可以预先计算它们。
So we basically pre compute them.
好的。所以这不是问题。
Okay. So this is not trouble.
好的，它们已经被计算出来了。
Okay, they are pretty computed.
然后我们提出了这个问题。
And we ask the question.
基本上，就是要计算这些数值需要什么。
So basically, what it takes to compute these values.
这里，si记住，它在目标范围内是一个零值，所以它是整数，
So here, si remember, it is a zero value in the target range, so it's integer and
QW是量化值，所以它也是整数。
QW is the quantitive value, so it's also integer.
为了在这里进行计算，我们只需要整数核。
In order to perform the computing here, we only need integer course.
这很好，因为就像我说的，整数核的浮点运算能力很高，
Which is good because like I said, integer course are pretty high flops
相比于浮点核来说，好吗？
compared to floating point course, okay?
同时，我们将累加这些数值。
Meanwhile, we are going to accumulate these values.
我们有加法和减法，对吧？
We have addition subtraction, right?
而且这些加法和减法也只在整数范围内进行。
And this addition subtraction are also performed only integer range.
所以我们仍然可以使用整数课程，这很好。
So we can still use integer course, which is good.
好的。实际上，通常我们在这里用一个位整数来表示这个值，
Okay. And in practice, usually, uh, here, we use a bit integer to represent the value,
但是当我们进行加法或减法时，我们会用32位来避免溢出。
but when we do additional subtraction, what we do is we use 32 bit to avoid overflow.
好的，有什么问题吗？对，QW是权重，对吧？
Okay. Any question? Yeah, QW is the weight, right?
这里我们讨论的是推理。
Here we talk about inference.
在推理过程中，我们不会改变权重，我们可以预先计算权重值，与值进行结合。
In inference, we don't change the weights, we can pre compute the weight value. Contact with value.
好的。那我们来看这个值，
Okay. Okay. Then we look at this value,
SW乘以X再除以Y。
SW time X divided by Y.
你还记得，这个值是一个浮点数，
You still remember, this value is a floating point,
它是在原始范围内的一个缩放比例。
It's a scale in the original range.
这很糟糕，因为如果我们直接计算这个值，
And this is bad because if we directly computer this value,
我们就需要用到浮点运算单元。
we are going to call floating point course.
这违背了去浮点化的初衷，因为在某些情况下，
That defeats the purpose of denation because in some scenario,
我的限制条件是没有浮点运算单元，
my codiation is that I don't have floating point course,
我只想用整数运算单元完成所有操作。
I just want to do everything integal course.
我该怎么做呢？实际上，很多神经网络中，这个值的范围在零到一之间，
How I do this. Empirical many nerNtw this value is in a range of zero and one,
因为它是一个缩放因子。
because it's a skinning factor.
人们通常采用一个非常“脏”的解决方案。
What people do is a very dirty solution.
所以他们并不是直接调用浮点运算单元来计算这个值，
So instead of directly calling floating point course to calculate this value,
他们基本上用的是一些定点乘法加上位移操作。
what they do is basically uh, they use some fixed point multiplication plus bit shift.
这个价格用的是以2为底的幂来表示数值。
This price represents value using power two.
当然，这个幂会是一个非常负的数值，再乘以另一个定点数，
Of course, the power is going to be a super negative value times another fixed point,
嗯，比如一个大约在0.5到1之间的小数。
um, like a fraction, which is around you half and one.
他们这样做的原因是因为定点运算
And the reason they do this is because fixed point is
计算成本比浮点运算便宜得多。
computation is much much cheaper than floating point.
你完全不用碰浮点运算单元。
You don't have to touch floating point course.
明白吗？而且位移操作也便宜得多，你只需要移动一下位就行了。
Okay? And also bit shift is much cheaper, you just ship the bits.
对，你在定点数里移动位，非常简单。
Yeah. Uh, you ship the bits in fixed point, which is pretty easy.
所以他们用这种类似于技巧的方法来近似这个值。
So they use this kind of like a trick to approximate the value.
好的。然后我们来看这个值，对吧。
Okay. Then we look at this value, right.
这个值是W乘以QX，而QX显然是依赖于输入X的，对吧？
So this value is W times QX, and the QX is apparently dependent on input X, right?
它必须要即时计算出来。
It has to be computed, uh, just on a fly.
W是权重的零点。
W is the zero point of, uh, the weight.
好吧？所以我们做的是，呃，呃，我们观察到很多很多神经网络，呃，呃，
Okay? So what we do is, um, uh, we observe that many many neural networks, um, uh,
它们的数值基本上是服从高斯分布的。
they are basically their value are basically following Gaussian distribution.
也就是说，它们的均值为零，特别是在训练和推理时。
That is, they have a zero me, especially a training raw inference.
所以与其去计算这个值，不如我们直接描述
So instead of calculating this value, how about we just describe
这个值，因为它们的均值为零，这意味着当我们尝试量化它时，
this value because they have a zero me, which means that when we try to quantat it,
我们也可以在一个范围内进行量化，并对齐零点。
we can also quantat in a range where we align zero point.
所以目标范围内的零点，在原始范围内也应该是零。
So the zero point at the target range should also be zero in the original range.
所以在这里我们可以假设
So here we can assume that
DW等于零，所以我们基本上可以这样做。
DW equals to zero, so we can basically im.
好的。我之所以这样，是因为零点，我们试图让它更简单一点。
Okay. I per, is because of zero, we try to simplify it a little bit.
当然，这其实并不准确，因为调整本来就不是很精确，对吧？
Of course, this is not accurate, by the way, because tuning is between not accurate, right?
你会损失一些精度，但只要损失不大就没关系。
You're going to lose accuracy, but it's fine as long as you don't lose too much, yeah.
是的。如果我们把EW等于零代入，就基本得到了这个方程，对吧。
Yeah. And then if we substute this EW equal to zero, and we basically get this equation, right.
所以你可以看到，其他部分都已经解决了。
So you can see, all the other parts have been figured out.
唯一需要重点处理的部分就是这一块，QW乘以QX。
The only heavy lifting part is basically this part, QW times QX.
这是什么呢？还记得Q和QX吗？
So what is this? Remember Q and
Q和QX基本上是在我的目标范围内对原始W和X进行的量化表示。
QX are basically the repent of the original W and X at my target range.
在我的例子中，它们是整数。
And in my example is integers.
所以基本上，这个QW和X是权重和X的整数量化表示。
So basically this QW and X are the quantit integer reptation of the weight and X.
如果我们把这两个合在一起，基本上就是在整数域上执行矩阵乘法。
And if we tape these two together is basically performing met mol in integer course.
所以这里我们用整数运算来完成主要的计算任务。
So here we are using integer courts to do the highway lifting.
这基本上达到了我们的目标。
That basically satisfies our goal.
我们的目标一方面是减少存储空间。
Our goal is to reduce, on one hand, we try to reduce the storage.
另一方面，我们试图把之前的浮点运算
On the other hand, we try to reduce the previous floating point arithmetics
转换为整数运算。
into integer arithmetics.
因为就像我说的，整数运算要快得多，成本也更低，还能节省大量能量。
Because like I said, integer arithmetic is much faster, much cheaper, save a lot of energy.
好的，明白。这基本上给你一个高层次的直观理解，
Okay. Cool. That basically give you a high level intuition,
这种近似量化基本上是做什么的。
what basically this kind of near quarantine does.
就像我一开始说的，你可以选择不同的目标范围。
Like I said at the beginning, uh, you can choose different target ranges.
所以在这里，如果你选择目标范围为LP8，你基本上就简化成了
So here, if you chose target range as LP eight, you basically reduced to
这个方程，其中QW和Qx都在LP8中。
the equation where this QW and Qx are in LP eight.
这意味着你可以把原来的LP16运算简化成LP8运算，
Which means that you can reduce the original LP 16 arithmetics into LP eight arithmetics,
这基本上就是DP sig所做的事情。
and that is basically what DP sig does.
目标范围是P8。
Target range being P eight.
好的，这一页幻灯片可以让你了解它在实际中的表现。
Cool. Okay, this slides give you a sense how this performs in practice.
的确，如果你使用这种近似条件，仍然可以保留很高的准确性。
Indeed, if you do this kind of near condition, you can still preserve much accuracy and
因为与Kems编码相比，记住在Kemi Cnation中你的计算速度会变慢，对吧？
because compared to Kems codon, remember in Kemi Cnation you are slowing down the compute, right?
但在近似连接中，不一定会这样。
But in near connection, not necessarily.
有时候你可以通过利用更低价格的课程来加速计算，好吗？
Sometimes you can accelerate the computer by leveraging lower pricing course, okay?
好的，这基本上就是本次讲座的结束。
Okay, that basically comes to end of this lecture.
我们来做一个快速总结。
Let's do a quick summary.
对于Nina条件，呃，呃，如果我们的目标范围是整数，我们基本上是用整数来表示
For Nina condition, uh, uh, if our target range are integers, we are basically represent
数据，对吧。
the data using integers, right.
我们尝试用我们的技巧和方法把整数恢复到目标范围。
We try to use our skill and point to recover integer into the target range.
对于算术运算，我们能够简化其中的一些步骤。
And for the arithmetics, we are able to simplify the little
一点一点地，最终我们就能上整数课程了，
bit and eventually we'll be able to integer course,
而整数课程比电话课程好多了。
and integer course are much better than phone course.
好的，明白，谢谢你。
Okay. Cool. Thank you.
我们周四在Zoom上见。
I'll see you on hasday on Zoom.
你不用来这里，去Zoom上就可以了，明白吗？
You don't have to be here, go to Zoom, okay?
好的。
Yeah.
嗯
H